<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/xml" href="/feed.xslt.xml"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><generator uri="http://jekyllrb.com" version="3.2.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-02-18T13:19:02-05:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Neha Kay</title><subtitle>Hi</subtitle><entry><title type="html">You Couchsurf? What’s that?</title><link href="/travel/what-is-couchsurfing/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You Couchsurf? What's that?" /><published>2018-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-29T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/travel/you-couchsurf-whats-that</id><content type="html" xml:base="/travel/what-is-couchsurfing/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This is Part 2 of the 8-part Beginner’s Guide to Couchsurfing:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;1. &lt;a href=&quot;/couchsurfing-guide&quot;&gt;Introduction to the Guide&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;2. &lt;em&gt;What Couchsurfing Is &amp;amp; How it Works&lt;/em&gt; &lt;br /&gt; 3. &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/getting-started-and-what-hosts-want/&quot;&gt;Getting Started and What Hosts Want&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;4. &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-write-a-great-couchsurfing-profile/&quot;&gt;How to Write a Great Couchsurfing Profile&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;5. &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/what-not-to-do-in-requests/&quot;&gt;Examples: What &lt;em&gt;Not&lt;/em&gt; To Do in Couchsurfing Requests&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;6. &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-write-a-great-request/&quot;&gt;How to Write a Great Couchsurfing Request&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;7. &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-make-sure-your-couchsurfing-experience-is-100-safe/&quot;&gt;How to Make Sure Your Couchsurfing Experience is 100% Safe&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;8. &lt;a href=&quot;/travel/is-couchsurfing-safe-for-women/&quot;&gt;Isn’t Couchsurfing Dangerous For Women?&lt;/a&gt;
——-&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;an-overview-of-couchsurfing&quot;&gt;An Overview of Couchsurfing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-couchsurfing&quot;&gt;What is Couchsurfing?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couchsurfing is a &lt;a href=&quot;couchsurfing.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; which allows you to connect with people in different cities and participate in cultural exchange for free by staying with them in their house, usually for 2-4 nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couchsurfing is perfect for people who are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Open-minded (to new people and ways of living)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interested in learning about the culture when traveling&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Flexible (if dates change)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Willing to spend less time at the touristy sites and connect with your host (grab dinner, go to an event, have an intellectual discussion etc.,) —&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you surf (e.g. stay at other people’s houses) there’s no obligation to host in the future, though many (including me!) often do host to pay it forward after many phenomenal surfing experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, there &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; an unwritten obligation to spend time with your host and get to know them. This could be through having a meal, chatting at their house, watching a movie, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some hosts are pretty hands off or are busy with work; others want to take you out and show you the city. It really depends on what kind of host you have, but in either case, be flexible, and be prepared to spend time with them if they’re taking the time out of their day to host you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-has-your-experience-been-like&quot;&gt;What has your experience been like?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a female solo backpacker, as of writing this post, I’ve Couchsurfed 31 times, hosting guests 10 times and surfing 21 times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A huge benefit of Couchsurfing is the ability to connect with locals. When I couchsurfed at  Cambridge University, for example, I lived like a student with my host, Jacky, a Cambridge student. We dined at a Hogwarts-style common room other travelers couldn’t access and my host even treated me to a &lt;em&gt;giant&lt;/em&gt; home-cooked feast with his classmates the day I arrived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next day, he took me to see Stephen Hawking’s office - an experience only a local would know of and access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/couchsurfing-guide/hawking.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, in the Czech Republic, my host had the most &lt;strong&gt;awesome&lt;/strong&gt; house and we spent a decent amount of time playing video games on his massive projector in addition to hanging out in person in the city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/couchsurfing-guide/czech.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He even later cooked me a vegetarian meal — which apparently is pretty unheard of in the Czech Republic (lol).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/couchsurfing-guide/czech2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, a couple years ago, a German surfer, Val, stayed at my place in Oxford University.
Unlike other travelers, he he had a chance to experience what it’s like living as an Oxford University student – again, an opportunity he had solely because he was Couchsurfing. I also took him canoe polo-ing – aka playing polo in &lt;em&gt;canoes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/couchsurfing-guide/cs-canoe.jpg&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the magic of Couchsurfing 😊&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-couchsurfing-free&quot;&gt;Is Couchsurfing free?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed Couchsurfing is free - free to stay with others for a few nights and free to host others in your place for a few nights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;is-couchsurfing-safe-arent-you-effectively-staying-in-random-peoples-houses&quot;&gt;Is Couchsurfing safe? Aren’t you effectively staying in random people’s houses?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s true that you’re staying in the house of people you haven’t met but references help make the experience safer. Each member of the Couchsurfing community has a profile which looks something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/couchsurfing-guide/cs-profile.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each member also has a set of references that look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/couchsurfing-guide/cs-references.png&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In general, if you stay with people with a large number of references and &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-make-sure-your-couchsurfing-experience-is-100-safe/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;take the proper precautions&lt;/a&gt;, indeed it’s pretty safe, even for women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, if you’re a woman traveling abroad, you’re concerned about safety. I’m a female solo traveler and I think about it constantly. I’ve written an entire piece &lt;a href=&quot;/travel/is-couchsurfing-safe-for-women/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; about staying safe as a female couchsurfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-is-the-incentive-for-people-to-host-others&quot;&gt;What is the incentive for people to host others?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Cultural exchange – meeting people all across the world and learning about their culture, ideas, thoughts, and ways of life.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Getting to know people you otherwise would never have known.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The value of helping other people out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meeting like-minded people.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having people to do fun things with / hangout.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Paying it forward if you previously surfed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it may be hard to imagine, there’s an incredible value of hosting someone at your house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve hosted 10 travelers and have had wonderful experiences with most all of them. Granted, one of them did smell bad (I had to keep my window open throughout his whole stay – LOL). But in all seriousness,through socialism vs. capitalism debates, chill conversations, and intellectual discussions, in every respect I’ve learned so much from each of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention it’s always great to be on the receiving end of gratitude. Most come with small gifts, acts of kindness (cooking dinner, buying dinner, etc.,) thanking you for your generosity. It’s nice to give back, especially when others have given to you in the past. This is the essence of Couchsurfing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-the-biggest-downside-to-couchsurfing&quot;&gt;What’s the biggest downside to Couchsurfing?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;it-requires-time-to-find-hosts&quot;&gt;It requires time to find hosts.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting hosts often requires sending 10 request for every 1 offer to host. If you don’t have the time to write personalized requests, you’re better off booking a hostel or hotel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;it-requires-research-and-being-careful-who-you-surf-with-and-host&quot;&gt;It requires research and being careful who you surf with and host.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure a safe experience, you really have to put in the time to request only people with a large number of reviews, reading the reviews, etc., If you prefer a quick booking experience, you’re better off booking a hostel or hotel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;it-requires-spending-time-with-your-host&quot;&gt;It requires spending time with your host.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most poignant difference between Couchsurfing and other forms of accommodation (hotels, hostels, AirB&amp;amp;B, etc.,) is the central unit of currency. In the latter it’s money; in the former, it’s time. While you don’t pay for staying at people’s houses, you do pay with time – spending time with them and investing in them as a person. This might mean not coming back at home at 1 AM (if your host isn’t a fan of that). Or it might mean eating dinner with your host instead of spending the entire night out. With Couchsurfing you invest time, rather than money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you Couchsurf, expect to spend time with your host – perhaps touring the city together, grabbing dinner, or having interesting conversations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;it-requires-being-flexible&quot;&gt;It requires being flexible.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, sometimes a host will cancel on you last minute. It’s only happened once or twice for me of 21 surfing experiences, but indeed, it’s a possibility. If you aren’t able to be flexible in these circumstances, you’re better off booking a hostel or hotel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;in-conclusion&quot;&gt;In Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine going to different cities, coming home to home-cooked meals, experiencing the city with friends your age, and having wild, unexpected and unequivocally valuable experiences.  This is the magic of Couchsurfing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continue to the next page in the guide:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/getting-started-and-what-hosts-want/&quot;&gt;Getting Started and What Hosts Want&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Other Posts in This Series:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/couchsurfing-guide&quot;&gt;Introduction to the Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/getting-started-and-what-hosts-want/&quot;&gt;Getting Started and What Hosts Want&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-write-a-great-couchsurfing-profile/&quot;&gt;How to Write a Great Couchsurfing Profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/what-not-to-do-in-requests/&quot;&gt;Examples: What *Not* To Do in Couchsurfing Requests&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-write-a-great-request/&quot;&gt;How to Write a Great Couchsurfing Request&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-make-sure-your-couchsurfing-experience-is-100-safe/&quot;&gt;How to Make Sure Your Couchsurfing Experience is 100% Safe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/travel/is-couchsurfing-safe-for-women/&quot;&gt;Isn’t Couchsurfing Dangerous For Women?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="travel" /><category term="travel - couchsurfing" /><summary type="html">This is Part 2 of the 8-part Beginner’s Guide to Couchsurfing:
1. Introduction to the Guide 2. What Couchsurfing Is &amp;amp; How it Works  3. Getting Started and What Hosts Want 4. How to Write a Great Couchsurfing Profile 5. Examples: What Not To Do in Couchsurfing Requests 6. How to Write a Great Couchsurfing Request 7. How to Make Sure Your Couchsurfing Experience is 100% Safe 8. Isn’t Couchsurfing Dangerous For Women?
——-</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Photos From 6 Continents &amp;amp; 30 Countries Abroad</title><link href="/photos/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Photos From 6 Continents &amp; 30 Countries Abroad" /><published>2018-01-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/footsteps</id><content type="html" xml:base="/photos/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;footsteps-abroad&quot;&gt;Footsteps Abroad&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Asia |&lt;/strong&gt;
China, Hong Kong, India, Japan, Malaysia, Myanmar (Burma), South Korea, Thailand&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Europe |&lt;/strong&gt;
Belgium, Czech Republic, France, Germany, Greece, Italy, Netherlands, Spain, Switzerland, United Kingdom, Vatican City&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;North America |&lt;/strong&gt;
Canada, Jamaica, United States&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;South America |&lt;/strong&gt;
Argentina, Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Ecuador, Peru&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Oceania |&lt;/strong&gt;
Australia&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Antartica |&lt;/strong&gt;
Coming soon ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;countries-ive-most-enjoyed-visiting&quot;&gt;Countries I’ve Most Enjoyed Visiting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In no particular order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;India&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Myanmar (Burma)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Italy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Thailand&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Argentina&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brazil&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;favorite-experiences-in-no-particular-order&quot;&gt;Favorite Experiences (in no particular order)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Myanmar (Burma) - The most epic people, super, super cheap, stunned by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.it/search?q=shwedagon+pagoda&amp;amp;source=lnms&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwixst_p5d7VAhXD0RQKHStSAqkQ_AUICigB&amp;amp;biw=1226&amp;amp;bih=780&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Shwedagon Pagoda&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ghana - Worked with and met some of the greatest people ever.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;United Kingdom - Studied as a visiting student at Oxford, what’s not to love?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Italy - The pizza, amazing architecture, amazing food…&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;countries-i-want-to-go-back-to---in-no-particular-order&quot;&gt;Countries I Want to Go Back To. . . (in no particular order)&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Argentina and Chile - So much to see + absolutely beautiful, need to visit Patagonia.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Brazil - &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; fun country (especially Rio 😛 ).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-awesome-photos&quot;&gt;Some Awesome Photos!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Photos of cool experiences abroad :)
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/1-autobahn.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This photo above was taken somewhere on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autobahn&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;autobahn&lt;/a&gt; — German highways with no federally mandated speed limit. 😉&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/Sal.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saying hi to Sal, the founder of Khan Academy and getting a bit goofy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/gangnam.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Me in the Gangnam district in South Korea! Yes, I did the Gangnam Style dance there, and no, I will not be posting that. 😛&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/jkrowling.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cafe where J.K. Rowling started writing Harry Potter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/underwater.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At Oxford, I once played underwater hockey which is about as crazy as it sounds. This is me before the game. It’s literally played on the floor of a pool, about 10 feet down with scuba equipment. The scuba equipment is so that you can watch the game while recovering your breath but the actual play is on the pool floor. When you’re back in play, you sort of dive down and get into the game — this is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=SAukrpTEvZA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;what it looks like under the water&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/9/9d/OctopushTwoPlayers28092009.JPG/300px-OctopushTwoPlayers28092009.JPG&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/border.png&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two images here are of me at the North Korean - South Korean border.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/dmz.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/4-kayak.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kayaking in caves in Phang Nga Bay, in Thailand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This also happens to be where the James Bond movie, &lt;em&gt;The Man with the Golden Gun&lt;/em&gt; was filmed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/2-scotland-st-patricks.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, I visited Dublin, Ireland on St. Patrick’s Day. Yep, and it was as insane as that sounded, and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you could imagine an entire city erupting in a party for 3 consecutive nights, that’s more or less what St. Patrick’s Day is like in Ireland’s capital city. These were some of the crowds during the festival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/8-paris.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This photo above of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arc_de_Triomphe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Arc de Triomphe&lt;/a&gt; is by far, one of my favorite photos. I had taken a bus (from Brussels, I think?) to Paris, but of course, it arrived &lt;em&gt;ridiculously&lt;/em&gt; early in the morning — around 6 am or so. And so I sort of shrugged, and figured I’d visit the Eiffel Tower, because, well, why not. On the way, I passed by this beauty, caught right as the sun was rising.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/napoleon.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Visiting Napoleon’s house and the Mona Lisa!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/bagan-sun.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the many beautiful temples in Bagan, Burma. This image was taken at sunrise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/bagan.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overlooking the ancient temples and ruins of Bagan, Burma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/equador.png&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Standing on the Equator!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/5-london-new-years.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Celebrating the 2014 New Year in London, across the Thames river.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/6-london-new-years-crowd.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the super crazy and super drunk London crowds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/7-burma-new-years.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the 2016 New Year in Burma! As explained &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.123newyear.com/newyear-traditions/buddhist.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“According to Buddhist traditions, no celebrations or festivals are considered to be complete until and unless one lights up candles in the temples and monasteries, as doing so is considered to be a symbol of showing love and respect to the blessed souls and to the supreme power. Also, it is considered to bless petitioner with good luck and happiness for the coming time. The same goes for New Year celebrations as well. On New Year day, people in Buddhist countries make a visit to temples and monasteries, bath Buddha statues, offer prayers and worship to Lord Buddha, and call for getting conferred with happy and peaceful times ahead.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/3-pichu.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Visiting &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Machu Picchu&lt;/a&gt; of the Incan civilization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/shibuya.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.gr/search?q=Shibuya+crossing&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;tbo=u&amp;amp;source=univ&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwiQ1rPMy-_VAhVpLcAKHWWrA3gQsAQIOQ&amp;amp;biw=700&amp;amp;bih=736&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Shibuya crossing&lt;/a&gt;, in Tokyo, famed to be the busiest intersection in the world. Find me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/3-canoe.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is us canoe polo-ing, which, believe it or not, is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=LPmxXt47XJU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;thing&lt;/a&gt;. It’s literally playing polo while canoeing. The picture below is me tipping over in the canoe — it’s actually incredibly hard to stay stable while trying to move forward with the ball. That whole week I was afraid some sort of swamp worm would have infected me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/4-c.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/brandon.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meeting Brandon Stanton of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.humansofnewyork.com/about&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Humans of New York &lt;/a&gt;. I heard he was coming to Hopkins to speak and made a point of making sure I met him before he left :P&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/shuya.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Tokyo host above was &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt;. He not only let me stay at his place for almost a week but also cooked me an &lt;em&gt;amazing&lt;/em&gt; traditional Japanese dinner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/9-colombia.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is overlooking the beautiful Colombian city of Bogota.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/10-london-crazy.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is me and Nicole being crazy, and totally contradicting the prim and proper British ways. 😛&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/11-czech.jpg&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Czech Republic, it was so interesting to see kids casually walking the streets alone — such a different cultural take than the American view of ‘kids walking alone is incredibly dangerous’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/shwedagon.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.gr/search?q=shwedagon+pagoda&amp;amp;source=lnms&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;ved=0ahUKEwjCuaLYxu_VAhWqD8AKHQ2mBacQ_AUICigB&amp;amp;biw=701&amp;amp;bih=736&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Shwedagon Pagoda&lt;/a&gt;, in Burma. Even after 28+ countries, the Shwedagon Pagoda is by far, the most impressive religious structure I’ve &lt;em&gt;ever&lt;/em&gt; seen — far more impressive than even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.gr/search?biw=701&amp;amp;bih=696&amp;amp;tbm=isch&amp;amp;sa=1&amp;amp;q=st.+peter%27s+basilica&amp;amp;oq=st.+peter%27s+bas&amp;amp;gs_l=psy-ab.3.0.0j0i30k1l3.55474.57301.0.58136.15.12.0.0.0.0.241.1305.0j7j1.8.0....0...1.1.64.psy-ab..7.8.1304...0i67k1.NHKf5NUWoLM&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;St. Peter’s Basilica&lt;/a&gt;. It’s simply absolutely &lt;em&gt;stunning&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/chang-rai.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wat_Rong_Khun&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wat Rong Khun&lt;/a&gt; in Chang Rai, Thailand. The entire structure is symbolic of Buddhist philosophy. As explained by Wikipedia:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“The main building at the white temple, the ubosot, is reached by crossing a bridge, “the cycle of rebirth”, over a small lake. In front of the bridge are hundreds of outreaching hands that symbolize unrestrained desire. The bridge proclaims that the way to happiness is by foregoing temptation, greed, and desire.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/13-scotland-volcano.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was a mountain I climbed in Scotland which would have been an awesome hike, had it not started snowing and hailing &lt;em&gt;super&lt;/em&gt; hard halfway up. Suffice to say, I still made it up and back down without dying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is an image of the mountain from afar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/13-2-sugarloaf.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/about-page/colosseum.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exploring the Colosseum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/15-spain.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was &lt;em&gt;the best&lt;/em&gt; pastry shop I’ve ever been to, in Madrid, Spain. Cakes and pastries to die for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe it was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tripadvisor.co.uk/Restaurant_Review-g187514-d2071743-Reviews-La_Mallorquina-Madrid.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;La Mallorquina&lt;/a&gt; that we went to, but I guess I’ll have to re-visit to be 100% sure. 😛&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/1-bigbang.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ve probably seen me wear this. A lot :P&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big Bang is probably the only artist I’ve ever had a super strong allegiance to, so naturally, I made it a mission to get a hat with BigBang’s logo in South Korea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But lo and behold, after about a week of searching I &lt;em&gt;could not&lt;/em&gt; find a hat with a simple BigBang logo on it — even in Myeongdong, the mecca for all things K-pop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So a couple weeks later, I ended up getting one made in Bangkok, Thailand, where it costs about $12 to make a custom hat. SO that’s the origin story of this hat. Only $12 of value, but took a great deal of effort to make :P&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/2-bb.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Big Bang concert! I ended up sneaking up to the front to see them a bit closer + had a camera with &lt;em&gt;epic&lt;/em&gt; zoom, resulting in this awesome photo. 😊&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/croc-min.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost got eaten by a crocodile :P&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/couchsurfing-guide/hawking.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Couchsurfed at Cambridge University, where my host took me to see Stephen Hawking’s old office.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/view.jpg&quot; width=&quot;300&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoying the view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/16-salinas-grande.jpg&quot; width=&quot;700&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This picture was taken at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Salinas_Grandes_(Jujuy_and_Salta)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Salinas Grandes&lt;/a&gt; in Jujuy, Argentina.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More photos &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/150567501@N07/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/photos-travel/ForevertheForeigner.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="life" /><category term="about neha" /><category term="photos" /><summary type="html">Footsteps Abroad</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Getting Stuff Done When You Have Absolutely No Motivation To Do Them</title><link href="/blog/getting-stuff-done-when-you-have-no-motivation/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Getting Stuff Done When You Have Absolutely No Motivation To Do Them" /><published>2018-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/getting-stuff-done-when-you-have-no-motivation</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/getting-stuff-done-when-you-have-no-motivation/">&lt;p&gt;This guide is part of the 5-Part Productivity Guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out all 5 parts in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/productivity-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Only Productivity Guide You’ll Ever Need&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Productivity Guide:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 1. &lt;em&gt;Getting Stuff Done When You Have No Motivation To Do Them&lt;/em&gt; — to get beyond one’s natural laziness/lack of self-discipline to actually get valuable projects done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 2: &lt;a href=&quot;/time-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Time Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — the ultimate guide on organizing time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 3: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/goal-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Too Many Goals? Organizing &amp;amp; Prioritizing Them&lt;/a&gt; — a system to organize macro-level and day-to-day goals within your time constraints.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 4: &lt;a href=&quot;/the-most-useful-productivity-insights-ive-come-across&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Most Useful Productivity Insights I’ve Come Across&lt;/a&gt; — a running list of great tips, resources, and links curated from other top sources to create a centralized productivity resource.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 5: &lt;a href=&quot;/note-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Note Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — how to actually organize the million notes you have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-this-method-is&quot;&gt;What this method is&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re the type of person who gets an idea and actually has the willpower/internal motivation/discipline to get it done —- then great! You can X right out of this guide because you really don’t need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you’re someone like me, who has a TON of projects and ideas but often little motivation to follow through and actually &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; them, then this guide is for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I generally have a ton of projects I love the &lt;em&gt;idea&lt;/em&gt; of doing, but on a day-to-day implementation level, have little motivation to follow through. In those cases, I use the system below to get around that. This includes doing the hardest intro to coding course, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs50.harvard.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harvard’s CS 50&lt;/a&gt; as a side project while doing a full courseload at Oxford University, waking up at 8:30 am on average in college despite having a natural tendency to wake up at 11 am, and following through on a bunch of side projects (like this blog!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-this-method-isnt&quot;&gt;What this method isn’t&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s not a quick skim or a list of 10 tips.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a long-form description of 3 full blown systems. Getting through the full guide will likely take a couple hours and setting up the system will take even more time. Proceed only if you’re willing to put in that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s not a cure-all.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone responds to expectations and work differently — that’s why there are &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; many different organization systems and productivity guides out there. Gretchen Rubin describes &lt;strong&gt;4 different categories in which people fall into based on how they respond to expectations&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upholders&lt;/strong&gt; meet both &lt;em&gt;inner and outer expectations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, if an upholder is assigned a work project (an outer expectation, held by his boss), they’ll surely get it done and get it done on time. If they make a commitment to &lt;em&gt;themselves&lt;/em&gt; (an inner expectation) to make progress on a personal project, they’ll follow through on that too. Example: Hermione Granger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obligers&lt;/strong&gt; meet &lt;em&gt;outer expectations but not inner expectations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people are obligers. If an obliger is asked to turn in an assignment by X date and time, they’ll surely turn it in by then. But if they give &lt;em&gt;themselves&lt;/em&gt; an assignment by X date and time, they’ll have a hard time getting it done. Obligers work best when there’s some sort of &lt;em&gt;external accountability&lt;/em&gt; present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questioners&lt;/strong&gt; follow through on &lt;em&gt;inner expectations and outer expectations which make sense to them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re constantly asking ‘why’ and digging 5 levels deeper into things to fully understand them before accepting or following through. In other words, if they want to do something, they will, but only if they fully understand why they’re doing the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rebels&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;resist both inner and outer expectations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They hate being told what to do and often times giving them a directive will make them disobey. When they do choose to follow through on something, it’s because they genuinely want to do something or because they feel it’s an important component of their identity. Example: Steve Jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This guide is written very much for obligers, and to some extent, questioners&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re an upholder or rebel, this guide is likely &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This guide isn’t about building motivation or self-control.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it possible to build self-discipline or motivation? I have no idea. What I do know is that developing self-discipline, self-control, or perseverance is &lt;strong&gt;hard&lt;/strong&gt; and takes time. Time that we don’t have when we have X, Y, and Z things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instead of placing so much importance on willpower and motivation, I think the better route is to find a way to change your environment or habits to make the change easier.&lt;/strong&gt; This guide is about exactly that — accepting one’s lack of internal motivation and &lt;strong&gt;still&lt;/strong&gt; getting stuff done by changing one’s environment through self-imposed accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-get-started---de-constructing-productivity&quot;&gt;Let’s get started - De-constructing Productivity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can deconstruct productivity by identifying the environments in which we are most productive versus the ones in which we are not. I think we can all admit our most productive intervals happen in the context of either &lt;strong&gt;work&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;school&lt;/strong&gt;. But why? &lt;strong&gt;Why do we tend to get an enormous amount of work done at work and school despite having little internal motivation to do so?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d argue it’s because we have 3 key elements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-clarity-in-what-needs-to-be-done&quot;&gt;1. Clarity in what needs to be done.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we’re not sure what needs to be done on a school assignment or problem set, we ask the professor or the TA until we have a clear sense of what needs to be done. In a work context, we’d ask our bosses or colleagues what a deliverable entails if there’s any amount of confusion. This clarity then allows us to better de-construct a goal or deliverable into more actionable tasks that we then proceed to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-clarity-in-when-a-deliverable-is-due&quot;&gt;2. Clarity in when a deliverable is due.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our boss or professor hasn’t provided a deadline for a deliverable, it tends to get put on the backburner in favor of other action items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More on this later, but suffice to say, having a clear notion of when something is due increases the likelihood it will be completed soon. Indeed deadlines can be incredibly motivating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-the-presence-and-awareness-of-consequences-if-an-action-item-isnt-done&quot;&gt;3. The presence and awareness of consequences if an action item isn’t done.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of school, these consequences of non-action present themselves as really bad grades (a consequence of not studying) and at work as a lack of respect from co-workers, a lower work evaluation, letting others down, etc. In both cases, the consequences are both &lt;em&gt;understood beforehand&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;severe&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide focuses on creating these 3 elements to &lt;em&gt;get shit done&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accountability-as-a-solution&quot;&gt;Accountability as a Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, when you’re not getting stuff done it’s usually because of one of these reasons:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. A lack of clarity of what needs to be done&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;em&gt;Goal Organization Guide&lt;/em&gt; focuses on this.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. A lack of clarity of the time one has to set aside for a task&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;em&gt;Time Organization Guide&lt;/em&gt; focuses on this. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. A lack of accountability for deadlines &amp;amp; quality of work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accountability is the &lt;strong&gt;invisible magical force that gets us to be productive in school and work despite lackluster motivation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, we end up working right up till the deadline and the night before, but &lt;strong&gt;we get it done&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-elements-of-accountability&quot;&gt;3 Elements of Accountability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A strict deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A set of consequences if a deliverable isn’t completed on time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A figure of authority enforcing the deadline and consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By nature, our home environments and personal projects lack all 3 of these elements. As a result, these projects get ignored when in competition with work or school deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because the latter has strict consequences for incompletion and a deadline, both of which we know will be enforced, unlike our personal projects which are er. . . more &lt;em&gt;flexible&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the solution is fairly simple: we need to introduce these elements into the achievement of personal projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-accountability-to-get-things-done&quot;&gt;Using accountability to get things done&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The crux of this system is having a friend hold us accountable to ‘turning in’ a set of deliverables by a specified date.&lt;/strong&gt; If we don’t, we have to pay up the pre-determined consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, we need the following elements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-an-accountability-buddy-whos-willing-to-hold-you-accountable&quot;&gt;I. An &lt;em&gt;Accountability Buddy&lt;/em&gt; who’s willing to hold you accountable.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This friend needs to be willing to enforce a deadline and a set of consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make sure your friend isn’t &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; close to you that they’ll let you off the hook easily.&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes, our friends are so close to us that they transform into inner expectations. &lt;strong&gt;If your friend/loved one is likely to let you off the hook if you don’t perform well, find someone else to hold you accountable&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re serious about getting things done, you have to be serious about the consequences if you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; get it done. That simply makes getting your tasks done more likely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ii-strict-pre-agreed-upon-consequences-if-deliverables-are-not-done-by-a-given-time-or-by-a-certain-standard&quot;&gt;II. Strict, pre-agreed upon consequences if deliverables are not done by a given time or by a certain standard.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What motivates you to get something done? Use that as a consequence. &lt;strong&gt;Financial incentives (e.g. paying a friend $10) work &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; well here. Why?&lt;/strong&gt; Because it makes you more likely to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the shame of not meeting a promise is sufficient – it really depends on what motivates you personally and what impact your friend’s view of you has on you and your motivation. Try it without money if you’re curious, ideally with someone who’s opinion of you matters to you. If that doesn’t work though, money almost always will ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think you might be unwilling to &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; pay if you fail to meet the deadline or deliverable standard, you can &lt;em&gt;pay your friend&lt;/em&gt; in the beginning (when setting up the accountability sprint) and have them return you the money only when you’ve met the standards. This is a lot less awkward than forcing your friend to make you pay them money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iii-explicitly-written-tangible-deliverables-with-fail-proof-ways-of-measuring-success&quot;&gt;III. Explicitly written tangible deliverables with fail-proof ways of measuring success.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More explicit deliverables make it easier to check if you’ve &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; followed through on what you intended to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your friend won’t &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; be able to measure your success if your deliverable is, &lt;em&gt;‘study for Calculus test’&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;‘read up on starting a startup’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the deliverable more specific, like &lt;em&gt;‘Read chapters 7-10’&lt;/em&gt; is better, but still sub-par; how will your friend &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; check if you’ve read?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, setting a deliverable of &lt;em&gt;‘Done problems 1-30 on pages 400, 450, and 438 each (90 problems)’&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;‘Read and took notes on chapters 7-10’&lt;/em&gt; are far better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iv-an-explicitly-written-form-of-submission&quot;&gt;IV. An explicitly written form of submission.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What format is the deliverable? Some good examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An email containing 4 graphs . . .&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A URL to X, Y, Z finished articles . . .&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Fitbit heart-rate tracking graph as proof I exercised for 20 minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A screenshot of 20 sent networking emails&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;v-explicitly-written-deadlines&quot;&gt;V. Explicitly written deadlines.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one’s pretty easy — something along the lines of &lt;em&gt;11:59 pm EST +/- 5 minutes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s generally a good idea to include a 5 minute grace period. The last thing you want is to lose $20 because you finished something 1 minute late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementing-an-accountability-sprint&quot;&gt;Implementing an Accountability Sprint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cool. Now that we have the ingredients of our accountability framework, we’re ready for an:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability Sprint&lt;/strong&gt; — a period of time when your friend is holding you to a deadline, and you’re in the productive zone of ‘sprinting’ to meet the deadline and deliverable standards and avoid the negative consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability Declaration&lt;/strong&gt; — this is the formal write-up of the deliverables, due date, and consequences that you’ll message or email your Accountability Buddy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give you a better sense of how to implement this &lt;strong&gt;well&lt;/strong&gt;, I’ll run through an example of converting a bad Accountability Declaration into a good one. I’d recommend you take a moment now to figure out what you’re trying to work towards and have a draft that you can modify as you read through this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-an-accountability-declaration&quot;&gt;Setting up an Accountability Declaration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-bad-declaration&quot;&gt;A Bad Declaration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I’ll email you statistics on distribution of wage/salary income of people with college degrees in metropolitan centers.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-its-bad&quot;&gt;Why it’s Bad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;its-vague&quot;&gt;It’s Vague&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what exactly does checking for “&lt;em&gt;distribution of wage/salary income&lt;/em&gt;”” mean? How do you quantify &lt;em&gt;‘statistics’&lt;/em&gt; into something checkable? How many metropolitan centers? There’s a lot of ambiguity that creates unnecessary wiggle room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;no-deadline&quot;&gt;No Deadline&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no due date associated with the task. By when? What time? You want the accountability declaration to be as specific as possible so that there’s absolutely no wiggle room (unless pre-outlined) on your end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;no-concrete-deliverable&quot;&gt;No Concrete Deliverable&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What tangible element is the friend going to check for? It’s unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;its-too-esoteric&quot;&gt;It’s Too Esoteric&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not in layman/easy-to-check terms. Unless your friend is a labor economics and statistics expert, she’s going to have a really hard time figuring out if you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; did all of the items above. And if she’s not sure, most people will likely let you off the hook, which is really bad because it compromises the integrity of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, you irritate your friend by asking them to parse through rather dense material, rather than giving them an easy set of things to check for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-good-accountability-declaration&quot;&gt;A Good Accountability Declaration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A better accountability declaration would be the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall Topic: Distribution of Wage/Salary Income&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliverable I: 4 bar graphs of the distribution of wage/salary income of Americans.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Delivery method: A PDF report, sent via email.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rubric: Check all 4 bar graphs are there, emailed on time, complete with detailed legend and a short paragraph explaining the data.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Consequence/Due Date: $10 penalty paid by Venmo if not emailed by 11:59 pm EST.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliverable II. A set of 4 mean, median, and quartile information blocks for each of the graphs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Delivery method: Sent in body of email.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rubric: Check all 4 sets of data are there (12 in total), emailed on time.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Consequence/Due Date: $5 penalty for each of the 12 data blocks, paid by Venmo if not emailed by 11:59 pm EST.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you see what a &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; change in specificity that is from the original declaration? Specifically, we parsed ambiguous terms like “statistics” into very checkable elements (mean, median, and mode information blocks) along with fixing all the problems listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-template-for-accountability-declarations&quot;&gt;A Template for Accountability Declarations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the following template when writing out declarations and mirror the specificity of the example above when writing Accountability Declarations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall Topic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deliverable I:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delivery method:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rubric:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consequence/Due Date:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-important-implementation-tips&quot;&gt;Other Important Implementation Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aim-for-week-long-accountability-sprints-not-longer--at-least-in-the-beginning&quot;&gt;Aim for week long accountability sprints, not longer  (at least in the beginning).&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My accountability sprints are never more than 1-2 weeks long. If you’re just starting out, it’s &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; important to have shorter accountability sprints for 2 reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you fail or mess up, you have less money on the line to lose. You don’t want to make a month long accountability declaration, get sick and thrown off schedule, and ended up owing a ton of money for missed deadlines. With shorter, week-long deadlines you have far less to lose.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shorter accountability sprints allow for more fine-tuning. The shorter the cycle, the more quickly you can change up what is and isn’t working (see the next tip).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shorter feedback cycles can be more rewarding. You meet the deadline quicker and therefore feel the euphoria of accomplishment more often. It’s pretty energizing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fine-tune-your-system-as-you-set-up-further-accountability-sprints&quot;&gt;Fine-tune your system as you set up further accountability sprints.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you overestimate how much you had to finish the first sprint? Then fix that for the next one. Were you not specific enough in describing deliverables? Fix that in the next one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since your sprints are only 1 week long, you can easily fix something that’s off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eliminate-as-much-ambiguity-and-wiggle-room-in-your-description-of-the-deliverable-as-possible&quot;&gt;Eliminate as much ambiguity and wiggle room in your description of the deliverable as possible.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of accountability declarations is to remove all possible wiggle room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? When we have trouble meeting a deadline, we look for wiggle room. We look for cracks in the veneer, for ambiguity, for the minimum possible we can do to still get credit. That’s just human nature and it’s &lt;em&gt;totally okay&lt;/em&gt; – it simply means we have to put in more effort in limiting the wiggle room at the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When I was in college, I desperately wanted to wake up earlier. So I told my friend I’d send her a photo of a “Hopkins workspace by 8:30 am +/- 5 minutes.” The problem with this declaration was that I was able to take a photo of a building 2 minutes away which was technically on campus masked as a workspace — this was invisible wiggle room that resulted in me getting to my &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; workspace at 8:45 or 9 am. Instead, the next time around, I became way more specific, pointing out that I’d send her a photo of “Brody reading room” — aka the actual workspace I meant to be in, thereby getting rid of the ambiguity and wiggle room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few minutes when you’re rushing to meet a deadline, you’ll look for all the possible ways you can undercut the deliverable while still getting credit. Acknowledge this habit in the beginning and address it by making water-tight accountability declarations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cool-accountability-examples&quot;&gt;Cool Accountability Examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-accountability-to-wake-up-early&quot;&gt;Using accountability to wake up early.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/accountability-guide/accountability-wake-up.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-accountability-to-meet-specific-personal-project--social-goals&quot;&gt;Using accountability to meet specific personal project &amp;amp; social goals.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/accountability-guide/accountability-wilson.png&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-accountability-to-exercise-daily&quot;&gt;Using accountability to exercise daily.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/accountability-guide/accountability-workout.png&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/accountability-guide/accountability-fitbit.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troubleshooting&quot;&gt;Troubleshooting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-friend-let-me-off-the-hook-is-this-really-that-bad&quot;&gt;My friend let me off the hook. Is this really that bad?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. yes. yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people let you off the hook for missing a deadline or a deliverable standard, it compromises the integrity of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the short run, it’s good, because you save how much ever money you put on the line. But in the long run, if you know you’ll be off the hook this time, you’ll figure you’ll be off the hook in the future, leaving room for you to slack off in future accountability declarations. This fundamentally compromises the very thing that makes the system work – an expectation of performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you tried it, and it failed, no problem. I’d recommend trying again, making sure you’re following all the tips above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-helps-me-get-work-done-but-how-do-i-make-sure-what-im-doing-is-high-quality-work&quot;&gt;This helps me get work done, but how do I make sure what I’m doing is high quality work?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve all experienced that feeling of cramming before a deadline — heck that may just be a routine for us. The fact of the matter is, &lt;strong&gt;accountability frameworks can guarantee that you’ll get something done well, but not necessarily done well.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you can quantify what it means for a deliverable to be done well – for example, specifying “4 bar charts” and further details about the charts, but often, it’s hard to perfectly quantify what our best work is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a weakness of the accountability framework largely because quality is largely dependent on internal motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to try and maximize both quantity and quality is to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perform an accountability sprint to get as much as I can done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the work is done, go back to add to the quality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continue to the next part of the guide:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/time-organization-guide/&quot;&gt;Time Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — the ultimate guide on organizing time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This guide is part of the 5-Part Productivity Guide.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out all parts together in the &lt;a href=&quot;/productivity-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Productivity Guide&lt;/a&gt;, or see the individual pages below:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 1. &lt;a href=&quot;/productivity-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Getting Stuff Done When You Have No Motivation To Do Them&lt;/a&gt; — to get beyond one’s natural laziness/lack of self-discipline to actually get valuable projects done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 2: &lt;a href=&quot;/time-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Time Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — the ultimate guide on organizing time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 3: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/goal-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Too Many Goals? Organizing &amp;amp; Prioritizing Them&lt;/a&gt; — a system to organize macro-level and day-to-day goals within your time constraints.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 4: &lt;a href=&quot;/the-most-useful-productivity-insights-ive-come-across&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Most Useful Productivity Insights I’ve Come Across&lt;/a&gt; — a running list of great tips, resources, and links curated from other top sources to create a centralized productivity resource.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 5: &lt;a href=&quot;/note-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Note Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — how to actually organize the million notes you have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="organization/productivity" /><category term="organization/productivity" /><summary type="html">This guide is part of the 5-Part Productivity Guide.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How to Maintain Your Network, Even on a Busy Schedule</title><link href="/blog/thoughts-on-how-to-maintain-relationships/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How to Maintain Your Network, Even on a Busy Schedule" /><published>2018-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/thoughts-on-how-to-maintain-relationships</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/thoughts-on-how-to-maintain-relationships/">&lt;p&gt;There are a ton of pieces out there on how to network and build one’s network.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But sadly, no one ever seems to talk about the people you have, and more specifically, how to cultivate &lt;em&gt;those&lt;/em&gt; relationships, instead of just making more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below is a description of how I personally keep in touch with my friends — it’s not necessarily the best way, just the way I happen to do it. If you have some ideas you think are uber cool and useful, feel free to share them in the comments section.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;background&quot;&gt;Background&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, this system is going to seem a bit crazy – the definition of going overboard. Who buys gifts for 20+ people or sends Mailchimp newsletters?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But I care a lot about maintaining my friendships and I’d argue the craziness of this system is pretty proportional to how much I care about my friends. Put simply, friendships are something I’m willing to spend time, money, and resources on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So &lt;em&gt;yes&lt;/em&gt; this system may seem a bit intense but you don’t have to replicate all of it — taking bits and pieces which you think would be meaningful to you works just as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As usual, I hope this helps and if you have any great (or better?) tips, let me know. 😊&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;elements-of-the-system&quot;&gt;Elements of the System&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My mechanism of keeping in touch with friends and maintaining relationships has 5 key components:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#i-a-mailchimp-email-newsletter&quot;&gt;A Mailchimp Email Newsletter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#ii-regular-videochats&quot;&gt;Regular Videochats&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#iii-birthday-phone-calls-emails-and-facebook-messages&quot;&gt;Birthday Phone Calls, Emails, &amp;amp; Facebook Messages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#iv-visiting-while-in-town&quot;&gt;Visiting in Person&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#v-miscellaneous-elements&quot;&gt;Miscellaneous Elements&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;i-a-mailchimp-email-newsletter&quot;&gt;I. A Mailchimp Email Newsletter&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yep, you read that right. A Mailchimp Newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I fundamentally think we all want to get updates from friends in ways that are not too personal but not too impersonal. We all have friends we’d love to hear from or would love to keep in touch but aren’t close enough to actually do this through means of messaging or texting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, while Facebook is far too impersonal and texting/messaging is far too personal, an email newsletter sits perfectly in between.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The feeling of being on one and in the ‘inner circle’ of the email newsletter is great, but it’s also not too extravagant of a motion because it’s quite obvious it’s going out to multiple people. In other words, it allows you to honor your 2nd and 3rd degree friends and provide them with a way of staying in touch with you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On your end, it’s simply easier to send the same update to many people, and still keep in touch with your inner circle via messaging. It’s literally the perfect solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally I have two newsletters segments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;segment-i-the-inner-circle&quot;&gt;Segment I: The Inner Circle&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the people I consider super close to me – the people who would truly enjoy hearing about my everyday life updates, including the more boring ones. Since these are people I consider pretty close to me, I’ll usually send out updates more frequently than the other segment — about every 3-7 weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;segment-ii-friends--acquaintances&quot;&gt;Segment II: Friends &amp;amp; Acquaintances&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are people who like you and are interested in you but probably don’t want to hear from you tooooo often. I generally send this segment updates every 2-4 months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-note-about-newsletter-segments&quot;&gt;A Note about Newsletter Segments&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that these segments can be dynamic — if you grow closer to a friend, naturally you can easily add them to your Inner Circle segment. On top of that, as you meet more and more people throughout your life, you can continue to add them and stay in touch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-implement-this&quot;&gt;How to Implement This&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make two lists on Excel – one of the people in your Inner Circle and one of the friends &amp;amp; acquaintances you’d like to keep in touch with.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create a &lt;a href=&quot;https://mailchimp.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mailchimp account&lt;/a&gt; and set up one list in Mailchimp (titled ‘Email Newsletter’). From there, you can &lt;a href=&quot;http://kb.mailchimp.com/lists/segments/create-and-send-to-a-segment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;create 2 Mailchimp segments&lt;/a&gt; for your Inner Circle and friend segments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Send update emails as frequently as you like!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;ii-regular-videochats&quot;&gt;II. Regular Videochats&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thing about relationships is that life gets in the way of them – &lt;em&gt;all the time&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friendships as a result, end up on the backburner, well behind career deadlines, watching Netflix, and romantic relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s almost as if we’re reactive to friendships, not &lt;em&gt;proactive&lt;/em&gt;. To avoid this, I make a point of scheduling regular phone or video chats with people I genuinely enjoy interacting with. Between my close friends, I’ll usually chat with 1-2 people every week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to making this work regularly with minimal effort is to &lt;strong&gt;schedule the next videochat at the current videochat&lt;/strong&gt;. If you don’t, you’ll have a great one-off videochat and you’ll forget to schedule the next one until sometime next year. Beyond that, this has 4 other upsides:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It reduces the awkwardness of having to message your friend a couple months later asking for another videochat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It makes the videochat &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; more likely to happen.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You don’t have to remember to reach back out in X months.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It leads to overall more communication.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-implement-this-1&quot;&gt;How to implement this&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Make a list of friends you genuinely enjoy talking to, who hopefully also enjoy talking to you. Reach out to them to schedule an initial catchup phone chat or video chat.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Towards the end of the initial video chat, say something along the lines of &lt;em&gt;“hey, it was awesome catching up! Let’s schedule another videochat – maybe in _ months?”&lt;/em&gt;. You can always move the time around closer to the date — it mostly functions as a reminder to videochat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iii-birthday-phone-calls-emails-and-facebook-messages&quot;&gt;III. Birthday Phone Calls, Emails, and Facebook Messages&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I make a point of remembering my friends’ birthdays and reaching out to them on their birthdays –– either with a personalized phone call, email or as a last resort, as a Facebook message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think it &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; goes a long way to do so and there are a number of tools I’ll describe below which you can use to better remember to reach out to people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-implement-this-2&quot;&gt;How to implement this&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I have a horrible memory, I’ve actually sat down and manually entered calendar reminders of my friends’ birthdays, which pop up on my calendar on the day of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various reminder tools you can use include:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Schedule friends’ birthdays in Google Calendar.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set up a &lt;a href=&quot;https://zapier.com/&quot;&gt;Zapier&lt;/a&gt; email notification based on a Google Calendar event.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Apple reminder system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This action has a high startup cost (sitting down and setting up reminders) but zero cost thereafter and I think taking the time to make a friend feel valued is &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; worth the cost of setting the system up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;iv-visiting-while-in-town&quot;&gt;IV. Visiting While in Town&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as you know you’re heading to a city, message the friends you know who live there. Nothing beats an in person meeting, especially if you’re willing to treat them to coffee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-implement-this-3&quot;&gt;How to implement this&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;1-have-an-organized-sense-of-where-people-are-located&quot;&gt;1. Have an organized sense of where people are located.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I maintain a spreadsheet of my friends, which includes a column for ‘city 2017’, allowing me to quickly look up the friends I have in a given city when I’m traveling. This allows me to not have to spend time figuring out who’s in which city every time I travel and more importantly, prevents me from accidentally forgetting to meet up with someone. 🙂&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;2-if-you-want-to-meet-people-you-dont-know-too-well-make-group-chats&quot;&gt;2. If you want to meet people you don’t know too well, make group chats.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend (shoutout to you, Nora!) did this when visiting New York from Oxford. I knew her as an acquaintance at Oxford and it would have been a bit of a stretch for her to directly message me to hangout, as we weren’t that close at Oxford.  Instead, she made a group chat with a close friend of mine and I, and on account of the close friend, I was totally down to come. That allowed Nora and I to solidify our friendship further, to the point where, if I was back in Oxford now, I’d be entirely comfortable meeting up with her individually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, this serves 4 functions:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It serves as a more efficient way of hanging out with people, especially if your time in a given city is limited.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It allows you to re-connect with people you may feel uncomfortable meeting one-on-one.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It incentivizes people who may not know you too well to feel comfortable meeting up with you.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It’s less talking pressure –– multiple people means it’s easier to listen / not have to talk, if you have an introverted side in you, like me =)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;v-miscellaneous-elements&quot;&gt;V. Miscellaneous Elements&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;generously-ask-people-for-advice&quot;&gt;Generously ask people for advice&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I have a problem, I’ll usually go ahead and message 5-6 friends and get their input on the matter. The benefit of this is 5 fold:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It sends a message that you value their advice and trust their opinion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;People &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; giving advice and you provide them with the opportunity to do so. In some sense, you’re giving people a reason to feel great by allowing them to provide their opinion.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;It sends a message that they’re important enough to you that you’d reach out to them for advice.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You get their advice on the matter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You create an environment in which they can come to you for advice and you can return the favor to them. There’s no better way of connecting with people than by helping them out!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s a pretty powerful ROI for one action item.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My friend recently called me for career advice on whether to move across the country and accept a full-time return offer at Goldman Sachs, the company she was working at. Over the course of an hour and a half, we worked through the problem and by the end, (I think) I was of help to her and on my end, I felt &lt;em&gt;way more&lt;/em&gt; connected to her than before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a sense, it was a double win for her; by the end of the day, she was able to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Get further insight on the issue bothering her at the time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Strengthen the relationship with each person she connected with.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(If you’re interested in reading more into this, this notion that asking others for a favor leads them to like you more is actually something that has been well researched and validated, coined the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.businessinsider.com/ben-franklin-effect-2016-12&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ben Franklin effect&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;actively-seek-reasons-to-connect&quot;&gt;Actively seek reasons to connect&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If people post about a new job or life event, I make a point of messaging them a huge &lt;em&gt;congrats!&lt;/em&gt;, and asking about how they’ve been since we last talked. It’s a great excuse to just reach out and say hi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, maintaining relationships for me is no small matter; it’s an active habit I maintain in life, as important and time consuming as maintaining my health and loving my family.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But it sure as heck pays off; I feel secure, loved, and supported and suffice to say, it’s been very much well worth the effort =)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Other Posts in the Career Guide:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/the-career-guide/&quot;&gt;Introduction to the Career Guide&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/to-what-degree-should-you-plan-your-career/&quot;&gt;To What Degree Should You Plan Your Career?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/6-ways-follow-your-passion-advice-falls-short/&quot;&gt;6 Ways Advice To ‘Follow Your Passion’ Falls Short For Millenials&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/thoughts-on-how-to-maintain-relationships/&quot;&gt;How to Maintain Relationships and a Network&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="career" /><category term="life perspective" /><category term="relationships" /><category term="career" /><summary type="html">There are a ton of pieces out there on how to network and build one’s network.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Too Many Goals? Organizing &amp;amp; Prioritizing Them</title><link href="/blog/goal-organization-guide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Too Many Goals? Organizing &amp; Prioritizing Them" /><published>2018-01-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/goal-organization-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/goal-organization-guide/">&lt;p&gt;This guide is part of the 5-Part Productivity Guide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Check out all 5 parts in &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/productivity-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Only Productivity Guide You’ll Ever Need&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Productivity Guide:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 1. &lt;a href=&quot;/productivity-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Getting Stuff Done When You Have No Motivation To Do Them&lt;/a&gt; — to get beyond one’s natural laziness/lack of self-discipline to actually get valuable projects done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 2: &lt;a href=&quot;/time-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Time Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — the ultimate guide on organizing time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 3: Too Many Goals? Organizing &amp;amp; Prioritizing Them&lt;/em&gt; — a system to organize macro-level and day-to-day goals within your time constraints.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 4: &lt;a href=&quot;/the-most-useful-productivity-insights-ive-come-across&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Most Useful Productivity Insights I’ve Come Across&lt;/a&gt; — a running list of great tips, resources, and links curated from other top sources to create a centralized productivity resource.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 5: &lt;a href=&quot;/note-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Note Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — how to actually organize the million notes you have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goal organization refers to 2 elements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Awareness of macro-level and micro-level goals and how the two relate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having clarity in how to achieve both goal levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goal organization is as idiosyncratic as time organization; some people have phenomenal systems using apps like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Omnifocus&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wunderlist.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wunderlist&lt;/a&gt; while others have equally great systems with just pen and paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this guide, I’ll go over my system — again, not necessarily the best one, but one that has worked well for me. If you have useful (or better?) tips, leave them in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this piece is to lay out different ways of representing goals and action items. If this is a system you’d like to adopt, remember that you don’t have to use all the methods described in this guide – the idea is to do only as much as you need to achieve clarity in what needs to be done at various scales in time – a semester, 3 months, a week, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s pretty much it by way of introduction. So with that, onwards, friend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;excel-spreadsheets-ahoy&quot;&gt;Excel Spreadsheets, Ahoy!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you’ll see below, I do all of my major goal, project, and multi-month planning in Excel spreadsheets. It’s versatile, free form, great for lists, and combined with my &lt;a href=&quot;/time-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;multi-month and month views&lt;/a&gt;, allows me to centralize all my productivity tools around Google Calendar and Excel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want any of the Excel templates of the layouts below, email me at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:nehakay8@gmail.com&quot;&gt;nehakay8@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; and I’ll send them right over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;macro-level-goal-planning&quot;&gt;Macro Level Goal Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; macro level goal planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It just feels super optimistic/inspiring/awesome — kind of like the start of a semester. Macro level planning is particularly great at the beginning of any new phase – a new semester, before starting a job, before a vacation, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-retrospective-reflection&quot;&gt;I. Retrospective Reflection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite method of macro level planning is imagining myself in the future, and thinking retrospectively about what I’d feel great having done or achieved. I ask myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Imagine it’s 8 months in the future and you’re thinking back over the last 8 months. You have a wide grin on your face because you’ve accomplished &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; you set out to accomplish. What did you accomplish?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it cheesy? Yep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it work well? Yep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll then go ahead and outline some vague goals underneath which might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Newsletter in motion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a successful website up and running.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Works and doesn’t shut down all the time.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Has a significant number of viewers/readers (&amp;gt;50-100/day).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incorporated into daily life – I naturally seek to write.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;(and more goals)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prioritizing--organizing&quot;&gt;Prioritizing &amp;amp; Organizing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you’ll likely have a number of goals – maybe as many as 7 or 10 depending on how optimistic you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being really straightforward and honest about why you want to get something done can be an insightful tool of getting to know yourself better and prioritizing goals. So for each goal, I often find it incredibly helpful to dig deeper into each goal with the following chart:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Mission&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Why is this important?&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Generic ways to accomplish mission&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Build a successful blog&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When creating missions, it’s better if your missions are &lt;em&gt;task oriented&lt;/em&gt; rather than outcome oriented. So instead of ‘Give a TED talk’ (something determined largely by the external forces of the selection committee), you could write, ‘Write a TED worthy compelling narrative / story’ or ‘Reach out to 100 TED selection committees’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can identify which of these goals are priorities by asking yourself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Say you could only accomplish 5 of these. Which would it be and why?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-macro-level-views&quot;&gt;Other Macro Level Views&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/goal-organization-guide/goal-org-guide-other-views.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, in addition to the reflective process above, I’ll lay out vague projects/goals/habits as they occur to me like the example above. Then, at the start of each month or at the end of a project, I’ll pick a to-do/project/thing-to-learn/habit to implement that month, and focus then on hammering out the details during that month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;micro-level-goal-planning&quot;&gt;Micro Level Goal Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, at this point, I have a great sense of the larger goals I want to achieve, but little idea how to actually achieve them in terms of day-to-day tasks. &lt;strong&gt;It’s time to make each goals actionable.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each project has an associated list of actionable to-do items. &lt;em&gt;‘Build a website’&lt;/em&gt;, for example translates into a 100 different action items, from &lt;em&gt;‘Research and pick a platform to develop on’&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;‘Get the favicon working’&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;‘Fill out about page’.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In other words, we need to streamline action on a project by listing out the more finely grained day-to-day actions that achieve a giant project.&lt;/strong&gt; These tasks need to be written in such a way that you could physically do them with no ambiguity about how to do them. Below are a couple examples of non-actionable tasks made actionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bad “Actionable Task” Example&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Good “Actionable Task” Example&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Study for Italian test&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Do 3 sets of Duolingo flash cards, read chapters 4 &amp;amp; 5 of textbook.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Exercise&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Do the 25 minute Jillian “Killer Buns” workout everyday for the next 6 days.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a macro planning session I like to lay out goals/action items per project with the following template:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/goal-organization-guide/goal-org-guide-project-view.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each project has a set of actionable tasks, arranged by how long it takes to complete each task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple quick notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can highlight cells of more pressing tasks in yellow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I usually order the tasks logically, so what needs to get done first is listed at the top.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have a lot of action items in the 5-8 hour column, it’s likely because they aren’t broken down into actionable sub-tasks. For example, ‘study for Data Structures test’ can be broken down into “Read Chapter 5, read chapter 6, etc.,” each of which go in one of the first three columns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this setup for a few reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;its-great-if-you-have-multiple-projects-youre-managing&quot;&gt;It’s great if you have multiple projects you’re managing.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organized by project/class allows you to pick and choose which projects are more pressing or which you’re more in the mood for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;its-helpful-for-seeing-what-you-can-get-done-in-a-given-time-period&quot;&gt;It’s helpful for seeing what you can get done in a given time period.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking tasks down by the time it takes to do them is helpful when deciding what to do on a day-to-day basis. If I have small blocks of time, I know I can grab tasks from the &lt;em&gt;Quick&lt;/em&gt; column and quickly finish them off during those small time blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, if you’re on the go, you can quickly see which projects you can complete on a train or in a different work environment. If you travel a lot, you could even add ‘Mobile Tasks’ as a column for each project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This view gives you a sense of 2-3 week action items, allowing you to perfectly filter out which of the tasks you want to take care of this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weekly-planning&quot;&gt;Weekly Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Project Pipeline view above, I’ll usually pick out all the action items I need to get done this week as a sort of free-form list of tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By that I mean, I’ll literally cut and paste the task’s cell from the project view into a separate ‘weekly to-do’ area. From there, I make sure each task is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incredibly actionable (e.g. no ambiguity of what needs to be done in order to cross it off the list)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Able to be completed within a 0-4 hour block. If it isn’t, I’ll try and break the task down into sub-tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a set platform for weekly planning – sometimes I’ll use paper lists, other times I’ll use my Mac Stickies app, other times I’ll plan each task out per day on my Google Calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-cool-views--planning-tools&quot;&gt;Other Cool Views &amp;amp; Planning Tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-done-category&quot;&gt;A ‘Done’ Category&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I maintain a “Done” Column to copy tasks into once I’ve finished them. Even though it’s easier deleting them, it’s nice looking back after a couple months and seeing your progress. Suffice to say, it’s a friendly reminder that achievement is simply the summation of small, seemingly unimportant tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brain-dumps&quot;&gt;Brain Dumps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brain dumps involve racking your brain for &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; existing project and action item, and getting it all on paper. They’re particularly great to do during a macro level planning session or in transitory periods (e.g. start or end of a work/school period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefit of this is simply not having to remember a million tasks in your head. There’s a huge amount of ‘carrying cost’ to store tasks, reminders, and to-dos in one’s head and it’s often times incredibly relieving to just sort of write them down and remove them from one’s internal memory storage. Use &lt;a href=&quot;http://gettingthingsdone.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/Mind_Sweep_Trigger_List.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this list&lt;/a&gt; as a starting point for your brain dump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-live-a-more-free-form-life--&quot;&gt;If you live a more free-form life. . .&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These past few months for me have been interesting simply because I have 8 months off to make progress on whatever goals I see fit before starting work at Microsoft. I’ve taken to listing out the general projects I’ll be working on each month, and then drilling down the actionable tasks that month itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/goal-organization-guide/goal-org-guide-month-goals.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/goal-organization-guide/goal-org-guide-essential-breakdown.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This guide is part of the 5-Part Productivity Guide.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out all parts together in the &lt;a href=&quot;/productivity-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Productivity Guide&lt;/a&gt;, or see the individual pages below:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 1. &lt;a href=&quot;/productivity-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Getting Stuff Done When You Have No Motivation To Do Them&lt;/a&gt; — to get beyond one’s natural laziness/lack of self-discipline to actually get valuable projects done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 2: &lt;a href=&quot;/time-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Time Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — the ultimate guide on organizing time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 3: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/goal-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Too Many Goals? Organizing &amp;amp; Prioritizing Them&lt;/a&gt; — a system to organize macro-level and day-to-day goals within your time constraints.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 4: &lt;a href=&quot;/the-most-useful-productivity-insights-ive-come-across&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Most Useful Productivity Insights I’ve Come Across&lt;/a&gt; — a running list of great tips, resources, and links curated from other top sources to create a centralized productivity resource.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 5: &lt;a href=&quot;/note-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Note Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — how to actually organize the million notes you have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="organization/productivity" /><category term="organization/productivity" /><summary type="html">This guide is part of the 5-Part Productivity Guide.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Parts of Aging You Wish You’d Been Warned About</title><link href="/blog/what-part-of-aging-do-you-wish-someone-had-warned-you-about/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parts of Aging You Wish You'd Been Warned About" /><published>2018-01-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/what-part-of-aging-do-you-wish-someone-had-warned-you-about</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/what-part-of-aging-do-you-wish-someone-had-warned-you-about/">&lt;p&gt;A friend forwarded &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/AskReddit/comments/6n2g3j/what_part_of_aging_do_you_wish_someone_had_warned/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this Reddit page&lt;/a&gt; which highlights what people wish they had known about aging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some particularly moving perspectives:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;time-starts-to-move-quickly&quot;&gt;Time Starts to Move Quickly&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My great grandma tried to warn me about this.. I didn’t understand at the time seeing as I was at my high school graduation party and time seemed endless. She said to me that when you’re young time seems endless you can think about your day in minutes that pass by. As you age you watch those minutes turn to what feel like seconds, hours will pass like minutes. In your adulthood you’ll see days pass like seconds on your wrist watch. I asked her how fast time passed for her, she told me how she would feel as if she felt like she lost months at a time as she day dreamed of her past.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The years are short, days are long.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;53 here. Your body will decline, yes, and if you don’t use it you will DEFINTELY lose it. Do something every day, even if it’s just taking a walk. But in return you gain something very valuable: wisdom and chill. Wisdom isn’t intelligence–it’s not like I turned 50 and could suddenly do differential equations. Wisdom is meeting someone and knowing just what their agenda is. Wisdom is being able to tell when someone’s trying to manipulate you and turning it around on them. Wisdom is realizing that when someone shows you their true nature, you should believe them. And you do get chill. The little things that drove you absolutely bugfuck when you were 25 are not worth stressing about. You think to yourself, “Do I want to die on this hill?” The answer is usually no. And you stop giving fucks and that’s wonderful. You give zero fucks about what people think of you because you’ve learned that, for one thing, people are pretty much only thinking about themselves, and two, you’ve lived your life as you’ve lived it and other people’s opinions haven’t affected it or you. They don’t have to live your life or live with your choices. You do. So do what you want with your life and what is right for you. I know people my age who did what was expected of them and now they are bitter and miserable and hateful. And they know (but won’t admit) that it’s their own damn fault and that they are stuck living the rest of their lives with the results of their choices.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The fact that I don’t feel older, it’s just that younger people seem even younger.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-parents&quot;&gt;On Parents&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That try as you may, you’re never fully prepared for your parents to get older. Somehow I still half expect my mom to be able to do certain things and it’s disheartening that she can’t. Even more so that she lacks the ambition and drive to do much.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My parents recently took me to where they have reserved their burial plots. The area is stunningly gorgeous, in the Colorado mountains, but the whole thing made me sad. Dad joked about him and Mom spending all of my inheritance money in the next 10-15 years. I looked at him and said, “Do it.” I want them to enjoy themselves, and that makes me happier than thinking about whatever money/stuff I’ll get when they pass on. Crap, their growing old still hits me in the gut.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;One of my scarier moments was the time I realized I was now stronger than my dad. We were moving some furniture and he took the heavier end out of habit, couldn’t lift it all that well, we switched sides after a few yards and I found I could lift that end just fine. We both knew what happened, but we never spoke of it. The silent shame of age.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This is a real moment for a lot of guys. When you are little, you want to be bigger and stronger than your dad, but when you eventually are, you kinda wish you weren’t.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;That try as you may, you’re never fully prepared for your parents to get older. Somehow I still half expect my mom to be able to do certain things and it’s disheartening that she can’t. Even more so that she lacks the ambition and drive to do much.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/aging-2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;550&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-hearing&quot;&gt;On Hearing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;OH! And you know all of those metal concerts??? Tinnitus is a bitch!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m 58 and was in broadcasting for 35 years with the headphones CRANKED every day for a 4 hour show and a 2 hour production shift. My nickname at work is “What?”.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Losing your hearing. I guess I was warned about it, but I had a desk job after college, and I spent a decade with earbuds listening to music everyday while I worked.
Now my hearing is fucked. I struggle discerning specific sounds in a crowded bar, to the point I don’t even try to converse with the people around me.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;It will happen to all of you youngins - as you start into your 30’s, you will notice your hearing starts to get a bit more challenging (along with other weird aches and pains that you realize may never totally go away).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-health&quot;&gt;On Health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The part where hurting yourself as a kid can have long term negative side effects. I played football in highschool only, had 4 concussions at least and busted both of my shoulders. Now in my late 20s I get migraines and the doctors said I have the shoulders you would find on a 80-90 year old man.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;By my mid to late 30s they said I will need a shoulder replacement on both arms ideally. If I knew that when I was 14 I would’ve done theatre or math club or anything that didn’t involve physical violence. I can barely sleep now because of the pain, I’d rather know how to act and sleep instead of saying I played football, it was a waste of time and now it negatively affect me every day.
Every. Day.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I played a least one season of soccer from age 4 to 22 every year and then some small leagues once I hit 24. Now sitting at 40 my right knee sounds like a bowl of Rice Krispy’s if I bend it just right.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I occasionally get depressed (nothing serious) about it. I used to be an avid runner and beach vollyball player. Now my body refuses to let me do either of them.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The part where all those broken bones, torn ligaments, injuries that never healed correctly, imperfect posture, terrible lift form… all build up and then eventually explode as you get older. It sucks.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You can often prevent, but rarely go back. It applies to skin, joints, and many other issues.&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;blockquote&gt;
      &lt;blockquote&gt;
        &lt;p&gt;Do this. My aunt lived in the sun/tanning beds and now looks like a leather handbag at 50. But like, a really shitty old one.&lt;/p&gt;
      &lt;/blockquote&gt;
    &lt;/blockquote&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;My sister refused to listen to my parents telling her to walk properly when she was a kid, walked on the side of her feet all the time, sat cross legged. Wouldn’t do shoes up properly just trod the backs down and shuffled everywhere. Refused to wear sensible shoes in her teens and tottered everywhere in heels. Part of it is a family issue with bunions and rotated toe joints, but a lot of it was down to her laziness and refusal to put the effort in to correct the problem.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;She now has chronic foot and knee pain, that is slowly spreading to her hips and back where everything is misaligned and just keeps getting worse.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;She’s 22. I dread to think what it’ll be like when she is actually old.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I always overlooked prevention and maintenance because I had “good skin”, or “good metabolism”, or “strong bones”, or “healed quickly”.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Today I write this with two knee surgeries from playing sports with no care to strengthen or recover, a spine that requires a lot of maintenance to function properly because of years sitting in front of a computer with bad posture, a few chunks taken out of my back because of years of not wearing sunscreen, GI issues from a terrible diet growing up. It pays to eat well, rest and take care of yourself. It took me too long to realize I was my biggest investment.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m only 28 but I wish someone would have said how important it is to stay limber. Just bending over in the morning I am so tight and stiff. Thank god it doesn’t hurt badly, yet, but I know hat’s right around the corner. I’m trying to get into yoga and stretch every night before bed.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Teeth. Take care of your teeth because it’s painful and expensive work if you need you’re whole mouth worked on just because you didn’t brush you’re teeth twice a day.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I’m turning 70 next year and I am in great health. Two reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I was a pussy when I was young. I didn’t do sports but I was in the Glee Club for 4 years (way before it was cool).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I was in the military at 19 and from that, worked out at a gym at least every few days. Did that for the rest of my life.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Now my BP is 120/80 +/- 2. My pulse is &amp;lt;80.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Not bragging here, but moderate exercise can prevent a bunch of problems. If you don’t have a workout routine with moderate weights and cardio, get going now. Even when my immune system went nuts for 3 years and I lost 50 lbs (from 210 to 160), I was able to workout and now that my immune system is back to normal I’m back up to 195 and healthy as a horse.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;There are plenty of great workout routines on YouTube and other places. Don’t waste a minute thinking about it. Do it, make it part of your life. You will NOT regret it.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Get used to being tired, always.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Pay attention to ailments that run in your family. Particularly cancer. Get screened early and often. An early colonoscopy could have saved me three rounds of chemo and three major surgeries.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-friendships&quot;&gt;On Friendships&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Finding friends as an adult is really hard.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;You’re dumped into friends in your youth, because you spend so much time with this set of people in school, for several years.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I was never particularly good at it then, but I have a hundred times the social skills now, and it is really damn difficult. If your coworkers don’t end up doing friendly things with you, you have to somehow, in between work, sleep, eating, and managing all of the other problems in this thread, go out intentionally to activities, repeatedly, trying to find people that don’t suck that also think you don’t suck, and then hope that your trying to become friends isn’t off-putting for them. You used to have 8 hours a day at school to do this, now you have to cram it into 1 hour, twice a week.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you made good, valuable friendships in high school or college, hold onto them the best that you damn well can. Because replacing them is a daunting task.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;on-looks&quot;&gt;On Looks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;This may be gender-specific (I’m a woman), but how the perception of your looks changes as you age. In other words, by the mere fact that I am visibly aging at all, past a certain age I become inherently less attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I would say that, up until my mid-20s and maybe past that, every year I seemed to get more attractive. I didn’t really change (I’ve always been pretty trim, with a good body, nice face, nice hair, etc.), but somehow I “grew into my looks.” I went from being someone who got a lot of attention but mostly bad, to someone who got a lot more attention, good and bad. Then as I got past 30, then 35, then 40, things changed a lot.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;I was still dating when I was in my 30s, but it became much much harder. Again, I didn’t gain weight, go grey, or even have any wrinkles, but I did look like I was in my 30s rather than my 20s. And the men who were interested in me would get older and older with the passing years. First mostly guys 5 years older would be interested, then 10. (I did meet some men who were my own age, one of whom I eventually married. He continues to think I am good looking – he’s also not too hard on the eyes).&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;This has also affected my work. I now work in the same place I did when I was in my 20s (left and came back about 15 years later), and it’s amazing to see how differently people, many of them the same people, treat me. When I was young, I often felt like I was the target of a lot of bad attention from the big men in charge. But I also didn’t realize that part of the reason they took me seriously (or acted like it) when they did was because they enjoyed having the attention and the approval of a young, pretty girl. As a woman in my early 40s now, it doesn’t matter that I wear the same dress size, have the same hair color and cut, almost the same face. I am still beautiful, but I’m old beautiful. I find these men take me less seriously than before, when I was a grad student, even with my big fancy PhD, publications, and grants now. Very odd.&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;TL;DR - Regardless of how objectively good looking a woman is and remains, many – if not most – women will just age out of the category of “pretty” or “beautiful.” They will not be considered ugly. They just won’t be considered at all.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of the quotes above were directly quoted from the thread &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/AskReddit/comments/6n2g3j/what_part_of_aging_do_you_wish_someone_had_warned/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="life" /><category term="life perspective" /><summary type="html">A friend forwarded this Reddit page which highlights what people wish they had known about aging.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Only Productivity Guide You’ll Ever Need</title><link href="/productivity-guide/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Only Productivity Guide You'll Ever Need" /><published>2018-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-24T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/productivity-guide</id><content type="html" xml:base="/productivity-guide/">&lt;p&gt;If you’re the type of person who gets an idea and actually has the willpower/internal motivation/discipline to get it done —- then great! You can X right out of this guide because you really don’t need it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But if you’re someone like me, who has a TON of projects and ideas but often little motivation to follow through and actually &lt;em&gt;do&lt;/em&gt; them, then this guide is for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I generally have a ton of projects I love the &lt;em&gt;idea&lt;/em&gt; of doing, but on a day-to-day implementation level, have little motivation to follow through. In those cases, I use the system below to get around that. This includes doing the hardest intro to coding course, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cs50.harvard.edu/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harvard’s CS 50&lt;/a&gt; as a side project while doing a full courseload at Oxford University, waking up at 8:30 am on average in college despite having a natural tendency to wake up at 11 am, and following through on a bunch of side projects (like this blog!).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-this-guide-is&quot;&gt;What this guide is&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This guide has 4 parts. Jump around to what’s most useful for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Part 1: Getting Stuff Done When You Have No Motivation To Do Them — to get beyond one’s natural laziness/lack of self-discipline to actually get valuable projects done.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 2: &lt;a href=&quot;#time-organization-guide&quot;&gt;Time Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — the ultimate guide on organizing time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 3: &lt;a href=&quot;#goal-organization-guide&quot;&gt;Too Many Goals? Organizing &amp;amp; Prioritizing Them&lt;/a&gt; — a system to organize macro-level and day-to-day goals within your time constraints.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 4: &lt;a href=&quot;/the-most-useful-productivity-insights-ive-come-across&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Most Useful Productivity Insights I’ve Come Across&lt;/a&gt; — a running list of great tips, resources, and links curated from other top sources to create a centralized productivity resource.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 5: &lt;a href=&quot;/note-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Note Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — how to actually organize the million notes you have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m also going to temporarily invent the word &lt;em&gt;‘unproductivity’&lt;/em&gt;, because it’s not a word when it really should be 😛.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-this-guide-isnt&quot;&gt;What this guide isn’t&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s not a quick skim or a list of 10 tips.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a long-form description of 3 full blown systems. Getting through the full guide will likely take a couple hours and setting up the system will take even more time. Proceed only if you’re willing to put in that time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s not a cure-all.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyone responds to expectations and work differently — that’s why there are &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; many different organization systems and productivity guides out there. Gretchen Rubin describes &lt;strong&gt;4 different categories in which people fall into based on how they respond to expectations&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upholders&lt;/strong&gt; meet both &lt;em&gt;inner and outer expectations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, if an upholder is assigned a work project (an outer expectation, held by his boss), they’ll surely get it done and get it done on time. If they make a commitment to &lt;em&gt;themselves&lt;/em&gt; (an inner expectation) to make progress on a personal project, they’ll follow through on that too. Example: Hermione Granger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Obligers&lt;/strong&gt; meet &lt;em&gt;outer expectations but not inner expectations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people are obligers. If an obliger is asked to turn in an assignment by X date and time, they’ll surely turn it in by then. But if they give &lt;em&gt;themselves&lt;/em&gt; an assignment by X date and time, they’ll have a hard time getting it done. Obligers work best when there’s some sort of &lt;em&gt;external accountability&lt;/em&gt; present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Questioners&lt;/strong&gt; follow through on &lt;em&gt;inner expectations and outer expectations which make sense to them&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They’re constantly asking ‘why’ and digging 5 levels deeper into things to fully understand them before accepting or following through. In other words, if they want to do something, they will, but only if they fully understand why they’re doing the task at hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rebels&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;resist both inner and outer expectations&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They hate being told what to do and often times giving them a directive will make them disobey. When they do choose to follow through on something, it’s because they genuinely want to do something or because they feel it’s an important component of their identity. Example: Steve Jobs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This guide is written very much for obligers, and to some extent, questioners&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re an upholder or rebel, this guide is likely &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This guide isn’t about building motivation or self-control.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it possible to build self-discipline or motivation? I have no idea. What I do know is that developing self-discipline, self-control, or perseverance is &lt;strong&gt;hard&lt;/strong&gt; and takes time. Time that we don’t have when we have X, Y, and Z things to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Instead of placing so much importance on willpower and motivation, I think the better route is to find a way to change your environment or habits to make the change easier.&lt;/strong&gt; This guide is about exactly that — accepting one’s lack of internal motivation and &lt;strong&gt;still&lt;/strong&gt; getting stuff done by changing one’s environment through self-imposed accountability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;lets-get-started---de-constructing-productivity&quot;&gt;Let’s get started - De-constructing Productivity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can deconstruct productivity by identifying the environments in which we are most productive versus the ones in which we are not. I think we can all admit our most productive intervals happen in the context of either &lt;strong&gt;work&lt;/strong&gt; or &lt;strong&gt;school&lt;/strong&gt;. But why? &lt;strong&gt;Why do we tend to get an enormous amount of work done at work and school despite having little internal motivation to do so?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d argue it’s because we have 3 key elements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-clarity-in-what-needs-to-be-done&quot;&gt;1. Clarity in what needs to be done.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we’re not sure what needs to be done on a school assignment or problem set, we ask the professor or the TA until we have a clear sense of what needs to be done. In a work context, we’d ask our bosses or colleagues what a deliverable entails if there’s any amount of confusion. This clarity then allows us to better de-construct a goal or deliverable into more actionable tasks that we then proceed to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-clarity-in-when-a-deliverable-is-due&quot;&gt;2. Clarity in when a deliverable is due.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If our boss or professor hasn’t provided a deadline for a deliverable, it tends to get put on the backburner in favor of other action items.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More on this later, but suffice to say, having a clear notion of when something is due increases the likelihood it will be completed soon. Indeed deadlines can be incredibly motivating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-the-presence-and-awareness-of-consequences-if-an-action-item-isnt-done&quot;&gt;3. The presence and awareness of consequences if an action item isn’t done.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of school, these consequences of non-action present themselves as really bad grades (a consequence of not studying) and at work as a lack of respect from co-workers, a lower work evaluation, letting others down, etc. In both cases, the consequences are both &lt;em&gt;understood beforehand&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;severe&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide focuses on creating these 3 elements to &lt;em&gt;get shit done&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;accountability-as-a-solution&quot;&gt;Accountability as a Solution&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simply put, when you’re not getting stuff done it’s usually because of one of these reasons:
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1. A lack of clarity of what needs to be done&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;em&gt;Goal Organization Guide&lt;/em&gt; focuses on this.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2. A lack of clarity of the time one has to set aside for a task&lt;/strong&gt; - The &lt;em&gt;Time Organization Guide&lt;/em&gt; focuses on this. 
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3. A lack of accountability for deadlines &amp;amp; quality of work&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accountability is the &lt;strong&gt;invisible magical force that gets us to be productive in school and work despite lackluster motivation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sure, we end up working right up till the deadline and the night before, but &lt;strong&gt;we get it done&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;3-elements-of-accountability&quot;&gt;3 Elements of Accountability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A strict deadline.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A set of consequences if a deliverable isn’t completed on time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A figure of authority enforcing the deadline and consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By nature, our home environments and personal projects lack all 3 of these elements. As a result, these projects get ignored when in competition with work or school deadlines.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because the latter has strict consequences for incompletion and a deadline, both of which we know will be enforced, unlike our personal projects which are er. . . more &lt;em&gt;flexible&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the solution is fairly simple: we need to introduce these elements into the achievement of personal projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;using-accountability-to-get-things-done&quot;&gt;Using accountability to get things done&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The crux of this system is having a friend hold us accountable to ‘turning in’ a set of deliverables by a specified date.&lt;/strong&gt; If we don’t, we have to pay up the pre-determined consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To do this, we need the following elements:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-an-accountability-buddy-whos-willing-to-hold-you-accountable&quot;&gt;I. An &lt;em&gt;Accountability Buddy&lt;/em&gt; who’s willing to hold you accountable.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This friend needs to be willing to enforce a deadline and a set of consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make sure your friend isn’t &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; close to you that they’ll let you off the hook easily.&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes, our friends are so close to us that they transform into inner expectations. &lt;strong&gt;If your friend/loved one is likely to let you off the hook if you don’t perform well, find someone else to hold you accountable&lt;/strong&gt;. If you’re serious about getting things done, you have to be serious about the consequences if you &lt;em&gt;don’t&lt;/em&gt; get it done. That simply makes getting your tasks done more likely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ii-strict-pre-agreed-upon-consequences-if-deliverables-are-not-done-by-a-given-time-or-by-a-certain-standard&quot;&gt;II. Strict, pre-agreed upon consequences if deliverables are not done by a given time or by a certain standard.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What motivates you to get something done? Use that as a consequence. &lt;strong&gt;Financial incentives (e.g. paying a friend $10) work &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; well here. Why?&lt;/strong&gt; Because it makes you more likely to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the shame of not meeting a promise is sufficient – it really depends on what motivates you personally and what impact your friend’s view of you has on you and your motivation. Try it without money if you’re curious, ideally with someone who’s opinion of you matters to you. If that doesn’t work though, money almost always will ;)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think you might be unwilling to &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; pay if you fail to meet the deadline or deliverable standard, you can &lt;em&gt;pay your friend&lt;/em&gt; in the beginning (when setting up the accountability sprint) and have them return you the money only when you’ve met the standards. This is a lot less awkward than forcing your friend to make you pay them money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iii-explicitly-written-tangible-deliverables-with-fail-proof-ways-of-measuring-success&quot;&gt;III. Explicitly written tangible deliverables with fail-proof ways of measuring success.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More explicit deliverables make it easier to check if you’ve &lt;em&gt;actually&lt;/em&gt; followed through on what you intended to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your friend won’t &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; be able to measure your success if your deliverable is, &lt;em&gt;‘study for Calculus test’&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;‘read up on starting a startup’&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making the deliverable more specific, like &lt;em&gt;‘Read chapters 7-10’&lt;/em&gt; is better, but still sub-par; how will your friend &lt;em&gt;truly&lt;/em&gt; check if you’ve read?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, setting a deliverable of &lt;em&gt;‘Done problems 1-30 on pages 400, 450, and 438 each (90 problems)’&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;‘Read and took notes on chapters 7-10’&lt;/em&gt; are far better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iv-an-explicitly-written-form-of-submission&quot;&gt;IV. An explicitly written form of submission.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What format is the deliverable? Some good examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;An email containing 4 graphs . . .&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A URL to X, Y, Z finished articles . . .&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A Fitbit heart-rate tracking graph as proof I exercised for 20 minutes&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;A screenshot of 20 sent networking emails&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;v-explicitly-written-deadlines&quot;&gt;V. Explicitly written deadlines.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This one’s pretty easy — something along the lines of &lt;em&gt;11:59 pm EST +/- 5 minutes&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s generally a good idea to include a 5 minute grace period. The last thing you want is to lose $20 because you finished something 1 minute late.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;implementing-an-accountability-sprint&quot;&gt;Implementing an Accountability Sprint&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cool. Now that we have the ingredients of our accountability framework, we’re ready for an:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability Sprint&lt;/strong&gt; — a period of time when your friend is holding you to a deadline, and you’re in the productive zone of ‘sprinting’ to meet the deadline and deliverable standards and avoid the negative consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accountability Declaration&lt;/strong&gt; — this is the formal write-up of the deliverables, due date, and consequences that you’ll message or email your Accountability Buddy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To give you a better sense of how to implement this &lt;strong&gt;well&lt;/strong&gt;, I’ll run through an example of converting a bad Accountability Declaration into a good one. I’d recommend you take a moment now to figure out what you’re trying to work towards and have a draft that you can modify as you read through this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-an-accountability-declaration&quot;&gt;Setting up an Accountability Declaration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-bad-declaration&quot;&gt;A Bad Declaration&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“I’ll email you statistics on distribution of wage/salary income of people with college degrees in metropolitan centers.”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-its-bad&quot;&gt;Why it’s Bad&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;its-vague&quot;&gt;It’s Vague&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what exactly does checking for “&lt;em&gt;distribution of wage/salary income&lt;/em&gt;”” mean? How do you quantify &lt;em&gt;‘statistics’&lt;/em&gt; into something checkable? How many metropolitan centers? There’s a lot of ambiguity that creates unnecessary wiggle room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;no-deadline&quot;&gt;No Deadline&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s no due date associated with the task. By when? What time? You want the accountability declaration to be as specific as possible so that there’s absolutely no wiggle room (unless pre-outlined) on your end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;no-concrete-deliverable&quot;&gt;No Concrete Deliverable&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What tangible element is the friend going to check for? It’s unclear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;its-too-esoteric&quot;&gt;It’s Too Esoteric&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not in layman/easy-to-check terms. Unless your friend is a labor economics and statistics expert, she’s going to have a really hard time figuring out if you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; did all of the items above. And if she’s not sure, most people will likely let you off the hook, which is really bad because it compromises the integrity of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, you irritate your friend by asking them to parse through rather dense material, rather than giving them an easy set of things to check for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-good-accountability-declaration&quot;&gt;A Good Accountability Declaration&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A better accountability declaration would be the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overall Topic: Distribution of Wage/Salary Income&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliverable I: 4 bar graphs of the distribution of wage/salary income of Americans.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Delivery method: A PDF report, sent via email.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rubric: Check all 4 bar graphs are there, emailed on time, complete with detailed legend and a short paragraph explaining the data.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Consequence/Due Date: $10 penalty paid by Venmo if not emailed by 11:59 pm EST.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deliverable II. A set of 4 mean, median, and quartile information blocks for each of the graphs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Delivery method: Sent in body of email.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Rubric: Check all 4 sets of data are there (12 in total), emailed on time.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Consequence/Due Date: $5 penalty for each of the 12 data blocks, paid by Venmo if not emailed by 11:59 pm EST.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you see what a &lt;strong&gt;huge&lt;/strong&gt; change in specificity that is from the original declaration? Specifically, we parsed ambiguous terms like “statistics” into very checkable elements (mean, median, and mode information blocks) along with fixing all the problems listed above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-template-for-accountability-declarations&quot;&gt;A Template for Accountability Declarations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the following template when writing out declarations and mirror the specificity of the example above when writing Accountability Declarations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall Topic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Deliverable I:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Delivery method:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rubric:&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Consequence/Due Date:&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-important-implementation-tips&quot;&gt;Other Important Implementation Tips&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;aim-for-week-long-accountability-sprints-not-longer--at-least-in-the-beginning&quot;&gt;Aim for week long accountability sprints, not longer  (at least in the beginning).&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My accountability sprints are never more than 1-2 weeks long. If you’re just starting out, it’s &lt;em&gt;especially&lt;/em&gt; important to have shorter accountability sprints for 2 reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you fail or mess up, you have less money on the line to lose. You don’t want to make a month long accountability declaration, get sick and thrown off schedule, and ended up owing a ton of money for missed deadlines. With shorter, week-long deadlines you have far less to lose.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shorter accountability sprints allow for more fine-tuning. The shorter the cycle, the more quickly you can change up what is and isn’t working (see the next tip).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Shorter feedback cycles can be more rewarding. You meet the deadline quicker and therefore feel the euphoria of accomplishment more often. It’s pretty energizing.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fine-tune-your-system-as-you-set-up-further-accountability-sprints&quot;&gt;Fine-tune your system as you set up further accountability sprints.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you overestimate how much you had to finish the first sprint? Then fix that for the next one. Were you not specific enough in describing deliverables? Fix that in the next one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since your sprints are only 1 week long, you can easily fix something that’s off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;eliminate-as-much-ambiguity-and-wiggle-room-in-your-description-of-the-deliverable-as-possible&quot;&gt;Eliminate as much ambiguity and wiggle room in your description of the deliverable as possible.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of accountability declarations is to remove all possible wiggle room.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? When we have trouble meeting a deadline, we look for wiggle room. We look for cracks in the veneer, for ambiguity, for the minimum possible we can do to still get credit. That’s just human nature and it’s &lt;em&gt;totally okay&lt;/em&gt; – it simply means we have to put in more effort in limiting the wiggle room at the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;When I was in college, I desperately wanted to wake up earlier. So I told my friend I’d send her a photo of a “Hopkins workspace by 8:30 am +/- 5 minutes.” The problem with this declaration was that I was able to take a photo of a building 2 minutes away which was technically on campus masked as a workspace — this was invisible wiggle room that resulted in me getting to my &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; workspace at 8:45 or 9 am. Instead, the next time around, I became way more specific, pointing out that I’d send her a photo of “Brody reading room” — aka the actual workspace I meant to be in, thereby getting rid of the ambiguity and wiggle room.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the last few minutes when you’re rushing to meet a deadline, you’ll look for all the possible ways you can undercut the deliverable while still getting credit. Acknowledge this habit in the beginning and address it by making water-tight accountability declarations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;cool-accountability-examples&quot;&gt;Cool Accountability Examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-accountability-to-wake-up-early&quot;&gt;Using accountability to wake up early.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/accountability-guide/accountability-wake-up.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-accountability-to-meet-specific-personal-project--social-goals&quot;&gt;Using accountability to meet specific personal project &amp;amp; social goals.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/accountability-guide/accountability-wilson.png&quot; width=&quot;800&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;using-accountability-to-exercise-daily&quot;&gt;Using accountability to exercise daily.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/accountability-guide/accountability-workout.png&quot; width=&quot;600&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/accountability-guide/accountability-fitbit.png&quot; width=&quot;400&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;troubleshooting&quot;&gt;Troubleshooting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;my-friend-let-me-off-the-hook-is-this-really-that-bad&quot;&gt;My friend let me off the hook. Is this really that bad?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes. yes. yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When people let you off the hook for missing a deadline or a deliverable standard, it compromises the integrity of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the short run, it’s good, because you save how much ever money you put on the line. But in the long run, if you know you’ll be off the hook this time, you’ll figure you’ll be off the hook in the future, leaving room for you to slack off in future accountability declarations. This fundamentally compromises the very thing that makes the system work – an expectation of performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So if you tried it, and it failed, no problem. I’d recommend trying again, making sure you’re following all the tips above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;this-helps-me-get-work-done-but-how-do-i-make-sure-what-im-doing-is-high-quality-work&quot;&gt;This helps me get work done, but how do I make sure what I’m doing is high quality work?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve all experienced that feeling of cramming before a deadline — heck that may just be a routine for us. The fact of the matter is, &lt;strong&gt;accountability frameworks can guarantee that you’ll get something done well, but not necessarily done well.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes you can quantify what it means for a deliverable to be done well – for example, specifying “4 bar charts” and further details about the charts, but often, it’s hard to perfectly quantify what our best work is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a weakness of the accountability framework largely because quality is largely dependent on internal motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to try and maximize both quantity and quality is to:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perform an accountability sprint to get as much as I can done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Once the work is done, go back to add to the quality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;time-organization-guide&quot;&gt;Time Organization Guide&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: same content as &lt;a href=&quot;/time-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Ultimate Guide on Organizing Time&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the Time Organization Guide! This guide is specifically for:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Feeling like you have time under your control.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a better grasp of the time you have to get work done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Not having to remember what you’re doing by when and outsourcing that information so you can focus on the things you actually need to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-basics&quot;&gt;The Basics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Time organization is one of those things that’s &lt;em&gt;highly&lt;/em&gt; idiosyncratic; some people have phenomenal systems using paper calendars while others love bullet journaling, while still are fine without even having a time organization system at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So do what works for you, and it may not be the system I describe here. That being said, if you’re like me, and like having things 1000% organized and laid out so you can focus on the tasks themselves, what you’ll read below is likely to be incredibly useful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;different-views-of-time&quot;&gt;Different views of time&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this guide, I’ll layout:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Multiple time layouts I find the most useful&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to set up a central time organization system around Google Calendar&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to maintain your central time hub&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-cautionary-note&quot;&gt;A Cautionary Note&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting up these different views and methods of planning takes &lt;em&gt;time&lt;/em&gt;. If you’re not willing to take the 3 hours or so it takes to set it up, you might be better off opting for a simpler system. That being said, I wouldn’t do it regularly if it wasn’t so, so, &lt;em&gt;so&lt;/em&gt; worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;macro-level-views&quot;&gt;Macro Level Views&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conventionally, most people maintain solely a weekly and daily view on time. And while you can map things out like this, I find it &lt;em&gt;incredibly&lt;/em&gt; useful to have both macro level (multi-month/month) views and micro level (weekly/daily) views. This is for a couple reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-time-simply-looks-different-from-a-multi-monthmonthly-perspective&quot;&gt;I. Time simply looks different from a multi-month/monthly perspective.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s far easier to get a sense of how each week translates to progress on major milestones (test, big deadlines, etc.,) than on a sole week view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ii-it-helps-you-translate-larger-goals-to-smaller-ones&quot;&gt;II. It helps you translate larger goals to smaller ones.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider the goal of studying for a test — it’s way easier to outline achieving this seeing a monthly calendar than solely the week leading up to the test.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;iii-its-a-wake-up-call-of-how-fast-time-moves&quot;&gt;III. It’s a wake-up call of how fast time moves.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As they say, “the days are long but the years are short”. The same goes for months and semesters; before you know it, it’s the end of the month or that massive deadline is approaching. In this sense, having a monthly view will keep you aware of how time passes on a macro level, rather than having it hit you in that final week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;different-macro-level-views&quot;&gt;Different macro level views&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on what period of time I’m in (for example, in school versus on summer break) I’ll maintain different macro level views. Below I’ve included 2 examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Macro views during school&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Macro views while on extended break&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;example-i--macro-views-while-in-school&quot;&gt;Example I | Macro Views while in School&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;_I’m currently backpacking Italy and don’t have access to my hard drive with these spreadsheets LOL. Will upload soon.__&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;example-ii--macro-views-on-extended-breaks&quot;&gt;Example II | Macro Views on Extended Breaks&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that I have an 8 month break, this is my current multi-month view on time, laying out where I’ll be in which month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/time-organization-guide/multi-month-view.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to that, I’ll have a view of the current month, which includes my whereabouts and often, what I plan to do on a bi-weekly basis in terms of goal-setting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/time-organization-guide/month-view.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-multi-month-and-month-views&quot;&gt;Setting up multi-month and month views&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-excel&quot;&gt;Use Excel&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I highly recommend setting up multi-month and month views in &lt;strong&gt;Excel&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s versatile, looks nice, and you can dedicate separate sheets to separate views and purposes. On top of that, if you use this system in conjunction with the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/goal-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Goal Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt;, you can also have your goals laid out in Excel as well. For example, have your multi-month view on one sheet, your month view on another, and your goals laid out on yet another sheet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bam! Your entire productivity system is now centralized between Excel and Google Calendar. Sometimes, it helps to print these views to PDF if you want an application that will open quickly, but otherwise, an exclusive Google Calendar and Excel system is perfect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;templates&quot;&gt;Templates&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Below are some templates which may be useful. If you end up downloading any of them, as a small favor back, comment that ya did so below! It makes a big difference to hear from you guys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2-Week Template&lt;/strong&gt; — download &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/template-2-week.xlsx&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Monthly Template&lt;/strong&gt; — download &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/template-monthly.xlsx&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Year Template&lt;/strong&gt; — download &lt;a href=&quot;/docs/template-full-year.xlsx&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From there, customize it by filling in the right dates. Enter major events like tests, major milestones, due dates, major problem sets, extracurricular events, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;micro-level-views--google-calendar&quot;&gt;Micro Level Views | Google Calendar&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For weekly and daily views, ALL HAIL GOOGLE CALENDAR!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Calendar will take care of your:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Weekly view&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Daily view&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Meetings with people&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Your day-to-day tasks and events&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is an example of how my calendar looked like in college:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/time-organization-guide/week-view.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Calendar isn’t that great for a monthly view as all the day-to-day events cloud out the big picture. That being said, if you wanted to use Google Calendar on a monthly basis, you could enter in big project due dates, tests, significant events, etc., as ‘all-day events’ in a calendar with a bright red color; this would make the important milestone events stand out, making the Google Calendar monthly view more usable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;setting-up-the-system&quot;&gt;Setting up the system&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-google-calendar-over-other-calendar-services&quot;&gt;Why Google Calendar over other calendar services?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google Calendar generally transfers better across devices and apps (for example switching from an iPhone to an Android phone is seamless via Google Calendar), is universally supported by every calendar add-on, plugin, or application, and has a number of import, export, sharing, and customizing options that Apple calendar or other services just don’t have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re already set up on Apple calendar or a written calendar journal and your setup is extensive, stick with that calendar platform. If you have a minimal setup or no setup, &lt;strong&gt;use Google Calendar&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-1--logistics-of-google-calendar&quot;&gt;Step 1 | Logistics of Google Calendar&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Head to Google Calendar &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.calendar.google.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and login or signup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-2--set-up-individual-calendars&quot;&gt;Step 2 | Set up individual calendars&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Individual calendars segment which events go into which ‘bucket of your life’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to maintain as many as 10 calendars for different elements of my life (e.g. exercise, school, friends, meetings, classes, etc.,) but I’ve found this is &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; too many. The transaction costs of A) deciding which calendar it should be in and B) clicking and setting up the event in that calendar way undermined the worth of having that many calendars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I now maintain 3-4 active calendars which works &lt;em&gt;way&lt;/em&gt; better:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Commanding Center&lt;/strong&gt; — This is the default calendar , used for any meetings with people or generic events. Unless my events fit better into a different calendar, they’ll go in here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Classes&lt;/strong&gt; — All recurring classes and tests go in here.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Me Time&lt;/strong&gt; — This is a calendar I use for any ‘self-decided’ activities — for example working on projects, sleeping, eating food, etc., are all classified as ‘me time’.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;(Career/Exercise/Social)&lt;/strong&gt; — In addition to the calendars above, it’s likely useful to have some calendars corresponding to things you value highly. During the job recruiting season, for example, I maintained a career calendar to distinguish all the recruiting events from the regular ones. If you’re super into exercise, on the other hand, it might be worthy to have a calendar dedicated solely to workout schedules. This is for you to customize and play around with. Other useful calendars may include: side project, learning music, office hours, etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/time-organization-guide/day-view.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Go ahead and make which ever individual calendars you think will be the most useful. If you need guidance on how to create the calendar, check out &lt;a href=&quot;https://support.google.com/calendar/answer/37095?hl=en&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this help link&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-3--set-up-google-calendar-on-the-go&quot;&gt;Step 3 | Set up Google Calendar on the go&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Download a mobile calendar app for mobile access – every major calendar app is compatible with Google Calendar. I use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/calendar/about/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;native Google Calendar app&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set up your mobile app to default to the day view; this way you can refer to your phone’s calendar for your day-to-day schedule (and presumably your laptop for the week and month view).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;step-4--maintaining-the-system&quot;&gt;Step 4 | Maintaining the system&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Everything&lt;/strong&gt; should go into your Google Calendar for 3 reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The whole purpose of organization is to have clearer focus on the hard tasks at hand. This is 10000x easier when you aren’t trying to remember which event you need to be at by when.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;By laying everything on your Google Calendar, you get an accurate sense of the free time you have. If half your events are off your calendar, there’s really little clarity gained with the items you do put in your calendar.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;You avoid decision fatigue of whether to put it in the calendar or not — instead, don’t waste time deciding – just take 30 seconds to enter it in and forget about it!&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All formal events should be added to Google Calendar. This includes classes, hangouts, videochats, office hours, work meetings, etc. In other words, anything which involves a commitment to another person should go into your Google Calendar — this way, as soon as you make the decision to meet up, you can literally &lt;em&gt;forget&lt;/em&gt; about it, as long as it’s in your Google Calendar and you check your calendar frequently.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Build the habit of always entering an event into your calendar and checking Google Calendar for your schedule.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s it for the time organization guide! If you follow those guidelines, you’re new and upgraded time organization system is ready to go. If you liked the Excel templates above, email me at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:nehakay8@gmail.com&quot;&gt;nehakay8@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; and I can send more over. Otherwise, make your own, get started, and have a ton of fun! Fill in below with any advice you might have that wasn’t otherwise said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&quot;goal-organization-guide&quot;&gt;Goal Organization Guide&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Note: same content as the post, &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/goal-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Too Many Goals? Organizing &amp;amp; Prioritizing Them&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goal organization refers to 2 elements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Awareness of macro-level and micro-level goals and how the two relate.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Having clarity in how to achieve both goal levels.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Goal organization is as idiosyncratic as time organization; some people have phenomenal systems using apps like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.omnigroup.com/omnifocus&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Omnifocus&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wunderlist.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wunderlist&lt;/a&gt; while others have equally great systems with just pen and paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this guide, I’ll go over my system — again, not necessarily the best one, but one that has worked well for me. If you have useful (or better?) tips, leave them in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of this piece is to lay out different ways of representing goals and action items. If this is a system you’d like to adopt, remember that you don’t have to use all the methods described in this guide – the idea is to do only as much as you need to achieve clarity in what needs to be done at various scales in time – a semester, 3 months, a week, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s pretty much it by way of introduction. So with that, onwards, friend!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;excel-spreadsheets-ahoy&quot;&gt;Excel Spreadsheets, Ahoy!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you’ll see below, I do all of my major goal, project, and multi-month planning in Excel spreadsheets. It’s versatile, free form, great for lists, and combined with my &lt;a href=&quot;/time-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;multi-month and month views&lt;/a&gt;, allows me to centralize all my productivity tools around Google Calendar and Excel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want any of the Excel templates of the layouts below, email me at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:nehakay8@gmail.com&quot;&gt;nehakay8@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt; and I’ll send them right over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;macro-level-goal-planning&quot;&gt;Macro Level Goal Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt; macro level goal planning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It just feels super optimistic/inspiring/awesome — kind of like the start of a semester. Macro level planning is particularly great at the beginning of any new phase – a new semester, before starting a job, before a vacation, etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;i-retrospective-reflection&quot;&gt;I. Retrospective Reflection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My favorite method of macro level planning is imagining myself in the future, and thinking retrospectively about what I’d feel great having done or achieved. I ask myself:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Imagine it’s 8 months in the future and you’re thinking back over the last 8 months. You have a wide grin on your face because you’ve accomplished &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; you set out to accomplish. What did you accomplish?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it cheesy? Yep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does it work well? Yep.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ll then go ahead and outline some vague goals underneath which might look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Newsletter in motion&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Have a successful website up and running.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Works and doesn’t shut down all the time.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Has a significant number of viewers/readers (&amp;gt;50-100/day).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Incorporated into daily life – I naturally seek to write.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;(and more goals)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;prioritizing--organizing&quot;&gt;Prioritizing &amp;amp; Organizing&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, you’ll likely have a number of goals – maybe as many as 7 or 10 depending on how optimistic you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being really straightforward and honest about why you want to get something done can be an insightful tool of getting to know yourself better and prioritizing goals. So for each goal, I often find it incredibly helpful to dig deeper into each goal with the following chart:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Mission&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Why is this important?&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Generic ways to accomplish mission&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Build a successful blog&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt; &lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When creating missions, it’s better if your missions are &lt;em&gt;task oriented&lt;/em&gt; rather than outcome oriented. So instead of ‘Give a TED talk’ (something determined largely by the external forces of the selection committee), you could write, ‘Write a TED worthy compelling narrative / story’ or ‘Reach out to 100 TED selection committees’.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can identify which of these goals are priorities by asking yourself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;blockquote&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;“Say you could only accomplish 5 of these. Which would it be and why?”&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-macro-level-views&quot;&gt;Other Macro Level Views&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/goal-organization-guide/goal-org-guide-other-views.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, in addition to the reflective process above, I’ll lay out vague projects/goals/habits as they occur to me like the example above. Then, at the start of each month or at the end of a project, I’ll pick a to-do/project/thing-to-learn/habit to implement that month, and focus then on hammering out the details during that month.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;micro-level-goal-planning&quot;&gt;Micro Level Goal Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, at this point, I have a great sense of the larger goals I want to achieve, but little idea how to actually achieve them in terms of day-to-day tasks. &lt;strong&gt;It’s time to make each goals actionable.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each project has an associated list of actionable to-do items. &lt;em&gt;‘Build a website’&lt;/em&gt;, for example translates into a 100 different action items, from &lt;em&gt;‘Research and pick a platform to develop on’&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;‘Get the favicon working’&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;em&gt;‘Fill out about page’.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In other words, we need to streamline action on a project by listing out the more finely grained day-to-day actions that achieve a giant project.&lt;/strong&gt; These tasks need to be written in such a way that you could physically do them with no ambiguity about how to do them. Below are a couple examples of non-actionable tasks made actionable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Bad “Actionable Task” Example&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Good “Actionable Task” Example&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Study for Italian test&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Do 3 sets of Duolingo flash cards, read chapters 4 &amp;amp; 5 of textbook.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Exercise&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center&quot;&gt;Do the 25 minute Jillian “Killer Buns” workout everyday for the next 6 days.&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a macro planning session I like to lay out goals/action items per project with the following template:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/goal-organization-guide/goal-org-guide-project-view.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each project has a set of actionable tasks, arranged by how long it takes to complete each task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple quick notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;You can highlight cells of more pressing tasks in yellow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;I usually order the tasks logically, so what needs to get done first is listed at the top.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you have a lot of action items in the 5-8 hour column, it’s likely because they aren’t broken down into actionable sub-tasks. For example, ‘study for Data Structures test’ can be broken down into “Read Chapter 5, read chapter 6, etc.,” each of which go in one of the first three columns.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like this setup for a few reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;its-great-if-you-have-multiple-projects-youre-managing&quot;&gt;It’s great if you have multiple projects you’re managing.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organized by project/class allows you to pick and choose which projects are more pressing or which you’re more in the mood for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;its-helpful-for-seeing-what-you-can-get-done-in-a-given-time-period&quot;&gt;It’s helpful for seeing what you can get done in a given time period.&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Breaking tasks down by the time it takes to do them is helpful when deciding what to do on a day-to-day basis. If I have small blocks of time, I know I can grab tasks from the &lt;em&gt;Quick&lt;/em&gt; column and quickly finish them off during those small time blocks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plus, if you’re on the go, you can quickly see which projects you can complete on a train or in a different work environment. If you travel a lot, you could even add ‘Mobile Tasks’ as a column for each project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This view gives you a sense of 2-3 week action items, allowing you to perfectly filter out which of the tasks you want to take care of this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;weekly-planning&quot;&gt;Weekly Planning&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Project Pipeline view above, I’ll usually pick out all the action items I need to get done this week as a sort of free-form list of tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By that I mean, I’ll literally cut and paste the task’s cell from the project view into a separate ‘weekly to-do’ area. From there, I make sure each task is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Incredibly actionable (e.g. no ambiguity of what needs to be done in order to cross it off the list)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Able to be completed within a 0-4 hour block. If it isn’t, I’ll try and break the task down into sub-tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a set platform for weekly planning – sometimes I’ll use paper lists, other times I’ll use my Mac Stickies app, other times I’ll plan each task out per day on my Google Calendar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-cool-views--planning-tools&quot;&gt;Other Cool Views &amp;amp; Planning Tools&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;a-done-category&quot;&gt;A ‘Done’ Category&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I maintain a “Done” Column to copy tasks into once I’ve finished them. Even though it’s easier deleting them, it’s nice looking back after a couple months and seeing your progress. Suffice to say, it’s a friendly reminder that achievement is simply the summation of small, seemingly unimportant tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;brain-dumps&quot;&gt;Brain Dumps&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Brain dumps involve racking your brain for &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; existing project and action item, and getting it all on paper. They’re particularly great to do during a macro level planning session or in transitory periods (e.g. start or end of a work/school period).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The benefit of this is simply not having to remember a million tasks in your head. There’s a huge amount of ‘carrying cost’ to store tasks, reminders, and to-dos in one’s head and it’s often times incredibly relieving to just sort of write them down and remove them from one’s internal memory storage. Use &lt;a href=&quot;http://gettingthingsdone.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/10/Mind_Sweep_Trigger_List.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this list&lt;/a&gt; as a starting point for your brain dump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;if-you-live-a-more-free-form-life--&quot;&gt;If you live a more free-form life. . .&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These past few months for me have been interesting simply because I have 8 months off to make progress on whatever goals I see fit before starting work at Microsoft. I’ve taken to listing out the general projects I’ll be working on each month, and then drilling down the actionable tasks that month itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/goal-organization-guide/goal-org-guide-month-goals.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;div align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/images/goal-organization-guide/goal-org-guide-essential-breakdown.png&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion-1&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And that’s pretty much it! If you have any questions &lt;em&gt;at all&lt;/em&gt; about implementing this, improving it, walking through accountability declarations — literally anything — email me at &lt;a href=&quot;mailto:nehakay8@gmail.com&quot;&gt;nehakay8@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;. I &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt; talking about this stuff and helping you work through it would literally be a hobby for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you liked this guide, check out the next page:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/the-most-useful-productivity-insights-ive-come-across&quot;&gt;The Note Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — how to actually organize the million notes you have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;and the post after:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/the-most-useful-productivity-insights-ive-come-across&quot;&gt;The Most Useful Productivity Insights I’ve Come Across&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This guide is part of the 5-Part Productivity Guide.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Check out all parts together in the &lt;a href=&quot;/productivity-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Productivity Guide&lt;/a&gt;, or see the individual pages below:&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 1. &lt;a href=&quot;/productivity-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Getting Stuff Done When You Have No Motivation To Do Them&lt;/a&gt; — to get beyond one’s natural laziness/lack of self-discipline to actually get valuable projects done.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 2: &lt;a href=&quot;/time-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Time Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — the ultimate guide on organizing time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 3: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/goal-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Too Many Goals? Organizing &amp;amp; Prioritizing Them&lt;/a&gt; — a system to organize macro-level and day-to-day goals within your time constraints.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 4: &lt;a href=&quot;/the-most-useful-productivity-insights-ive-come-across&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Most Useful Productivity Insights I’ve Come Across&lt;/a&gt; — a running list of great tips, resources, and links curated from other top sources to create a centralized productivity resource.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 5: &lt;a href=&quot;/note-organization-guide/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Note Organization Guide&lt;/a&gt; — how to actually organize the million notes you have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="organization/productivity" /><category term="organization/productivity" /><summary type="html">If you’re the type of person who gets an idea and actually has the willpower/internal motivation/discipline to get it done —- then great! You can X right out of this guide because you really don’t need it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Beginner’s Guide to Couchsurfing - How to Couchsurf</title><link href="/couchsurfing-guide" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Beginner's Guide to Couchsurfing - How to Couchsurf" /><published>2018-01-23T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-23T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/beginners-guide-to-couchsurfing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/couchsurfing-guide">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Welcome to the Beginner’s Couchsurfing Guide!&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having backpacked and couchsurfed in 28 countries, I’ve learned the ins and outs of the system and have taken the time to write them down in an 8 part guide. But I’m just one human. So, to add to my knowledge, I’ve also interviewed a number of more experienced Couchsurfers (e.g. 200+ reviewed Couchsurfers) for their tips and insights, which are included in this guide as well. You won’t find a guide that’s better or more comprehensive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardest part about Couchsurfing is undoubtedly getting started. You want to get hosted. But you have no reviews. How do you get hosts if hosts only accept people with reviews? Seems like quite the closed circle. It can be, and a number of people struggle to find hosts on Couchsurfing. That being said, if you take the time to read through the guide, by the end, you’ll have no trouble whatsoever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This guide covers a ton of stuff. Skip around to what’s most useful for you:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 1: The Beginner’s Guide to Couchsurfing - How to Couchsurf (this page)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 2: &lt;a href=&quot;/travel/what-is-couchsurfing/&quot;&gt;What Couchsurfing Is &amp;amp; How it Works&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 3: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/getting-started-and-what-hosts-want/&quot;&gt;Getting Started and What Hosts Want&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 4: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-write-a-great-couchsurfing-profile/&quot;&gt;How to Write a Great Couchsurfing Profile&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 5: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/what-not-to-do-in-requests/&quot;&gt;Examples: What &lt;em&gt;Not&lt;/em&gt; To Do&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 6: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-write-a-great-request/&quot;&gt;How to Write a Great Request&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 7: &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-to-make-sure-your-couchsurfing-experience-is-100-safe/&quot;&gt;How to Make Sure Your Couchsurfing Experience is 100% Safe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Part 8: &lt;a href=&quot;/travel/is-couchsurfing-safe-for-women/&quot;&gt;Isn’t Couchsurfing Dangerous For Women?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you’re totally new to Couchsurfing:&lt;/strong&gt; read more about &lt;a href=&quot;/travel/what-is-couchsurfing/&quot;&gt;what it is and how it works here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If you already have a good sense of what Couchsurfing is and just want to know how to write better requests:&lt;/strong&gt; skip the overview and head to &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/getting-started-and-what-hosts-want/&quot;&gt;Getting Started and What Hosts Want&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="travel" /><category term="travel - couchsurfing" /><summary type="html">Welcome to the Beginner’s Couchsurfing Guide!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Finite Fucks Theory</title><link href="/blog/finite-fucks-theory/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Finite Fucks Theory" /><published>2017-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/finite-fucks-theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/finite-fucks-theory/">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#&quot; class=&quot;image main&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/posts/finite-fucks-theory.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brought to you by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reddit.com/r/AskReddit/comments/6n2g3j/what_part_of_aging_do_you_wish_someone_had_warned/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Reddit&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="life" /><category term="life perspective" /><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Favorite Books, Blogs, Articles, and Podcasts</title><link href="/blog/favorites/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Favorite Books, Blogs, Articles, and Podcasts" /><published>2017-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2017-11-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/blog/favorites</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/favorites/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;navigate-the-favorites&quot;&gt;Navigate the Favorites&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#favorite-books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/quotes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Quotes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#favorite-blogs&quot;&gt;Blogs&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#favorite-articles&quot;&gt;Articles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#favorite-podcasts&quot;&gt;Podcasts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#favorite-podcast-episodes&quot;&gt;Podcast Episodes&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;favorite-books&quot;&gt;Favorite Books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got a whole post dedicated to this! Check it out &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/favorite-books/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;favorite-quotes&quot;&gt;Favorite Quotes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Got a whole post dedicated to this! Check it out &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/quotes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;favorite-blogs&quot;&gt;Favorite Blogs&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wait But Why&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A long-form blog which analyzes all aspects of life and technology.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.paulgraham.com/articles.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Paul Graham’s Essays&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://jamesclear.com/articles&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;James Clear&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces on productivity, habits and organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://markmanson.net&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mark Manson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Pieces on productivity, habits and organization.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;favorite-articles&quot;&gt;Favorite Articles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;life-perspective&quot;&gt;Life Perspective&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com/2015/12/the-tail-end.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Tail End&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;habits--productivity--positive-psychology&quot;&gt;Habits / Productivity / Positive Psychology&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/startup-grind/how-to-start-a-company-with-no-free-time-b70fbe7b918a&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How to Start a Company With No Free Time&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.becomingminimalist.com/look/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;If You Are Looking for Reasons to Be Happy, You’ll Probably Find Them&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;feminism&quot;&gt;Feminism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2015/10/why-i-put-my-wifes-career-first/403240/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Why I Put My Wife’s Career First&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/2016/8/1/12108126/gender-wage-gap-explained-real&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The truth about the gender wage gap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;career&quot;&gt;Career&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://qz.com/640112/the-career-advice-no-one-tells-you/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Career Advice No One Tells You&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://calnewport.com/blog/2013/07/03/why-did-most-of-dartmouths-valedictorians-become-investment-bankers-and-consultants-the-need-for-a-deeper-vocabulary-of-career-aspiration/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Why Did Most of Dartmouth’s Valedictorians Become Investment Bankers and Consultants? The Need for a Deeper Vocabulary of Career Aspiration&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/06/05/jobs/graduating-and-looking-for-your-passion-just-be-patient.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Graduating and Looking for Your Passion? Just Be Patient&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/09/11/upshot/how-to-become-a-ceo-the-quickest-path-is-a-winding-one.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How to Become a C.E.O.? The Quickest Path Is a Winding One&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;health&quot;&gt;Health&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/05/02/health/biggest-loser-weight-loss.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;After ‘The Biggest Loser, Their Bodies Fought to Regain Weight&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;romantic-relationships&quot;&gt;Romantic Relationships&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://waitbutwhy.com/2014/02/pick-life-partner-part-2.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How to Pick Your Life Partner&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/01/11/fashion/modern-love-to-fall-in-love-with-anyone-do-this.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;To Fall in Love With Anyone, Do This&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://markmanson.net/relationship-advice&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1,500 People Give All The Relationship Advice You’ll Ever Need&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thecut.com/2016/02/what-romance-means-after-10-years-of-marriage.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;What Romance Really Means After 10 Years of Marriage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2015/07/20/fashion/modern-love-redux-readers-offer-their-own-honest-thoughts-on-marriage.html?smid=fb-nytimes&amp;amp;smtyp=cur&amp;amp;assetType=nyt_now&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Modern Love Redux: Readers Offer Their Own Honest Thoughts on Marriage&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/06/23/style/modern-love-to-stay-in-love-sign-on-the-dotted-line-36-questions.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;To Stay in Love, Sign on the Dotted Line&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;friendships&quot;&gt;Friendships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/health/archive/2015/10/how-friendships-change-over-time-in-adulthood/411466/?utm_source=pocket&amp;amp;utm_medium=email&amp;amp;utm_campaign=pockethits&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How Friendships Change in Adulthood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;favorite-podcasts&quot;&gt;Favorite Podcasts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Descriptions copied below from each podcast’s website)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;life-perspective-1&quot;&gt;Life Perspective&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gretchenrubin.com/podcast/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Happier with Gretchen Rubin&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A podcast hosted by best-selling author Gretchen Rubin and TV writer and producer, Elizabeth Craft which discusses happiness, good habits, and human nature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://happierinhollywood.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Happier in Hollywood&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How to be happier, saner, more creative, more successful, and more productive in a back-biting, superficial, chaotic, unpredictable, and fundamentally insane world.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.npr.org/podcasts/510307/invisibilia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Invisibilia&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Invisibilia is about the invisible forces that control human behavior - ideas, beliefs, assumptions, and emotions.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;didactic&quot;&gt;Didactic&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;freakonomics.com/archive/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Freakonomics Radio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Each week, hear surprising conversations that explore the riddles of everyday life and the weird wrinkles of human nature — from cheating to crime to parenting and sports. Dubner talks with Nobel laureates and provocateurs, social scientists and entrepreneurs.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;revisionisthistory.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Revisionist History&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Malcolm Gladwell’s journey through the overlooked and the misunderstood. Every episode re-examines something from the past — an event, a person, an idea, even a song — and asks whether we got it right the first time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;career-1&quot;&gt;Career&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;www.npr.org/podcasts/510313/how-i-built-this&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How I Built This&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A podcast about innovators, entrepreneurs, and idealists, and the stories behind the movements they built. Each episode is a narrative journey marked by triumphs, failures, serendipity, and insight — told by the founders of some of the world’s best known companies and brands.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.acast.com/howididit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Success! How I Did It&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Shontell interviews successful CEOs, entrepreneurs, and business leaders about how they built successful companies, and the career paths that took them to the top.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-relationships&quot;&gt;On Relationships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.estherperel.com/podcast&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Where Should We Begin?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Real couples. Candid conversations. Surprising truths. Listen in as the foremost authority on modern love, Esther Perel, meets with real couples — and their stories become your stories.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;other&quot;&gt;Other&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sidehustleschool.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Side Hustle School&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A daily show for everyone who works a regular job and wants to start an income-earning project on the side. In each episode, listeners will hear a different story of someone who’s started a side hustle — along with what went well, how that person overcame challenges, and what happened as a result.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.earhustlesq.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ear Hustle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Ear Hustle brings you the stories of life inside prison, shared and produced by those living it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;favorite-podcast-episodes&quot;&gt;Favorite Podcast Episodes&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://itunes.apple.com/us/podcast/how-i-built-this/id1150510297?mt=2&amp;amp;i=375191888&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;How I Built This - Sara Blakely&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://gretchenrubin.com/happiness_project/2016/06/podcast-70-best-advice/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Happier: What’s the Best Advice You’ve Ever Gotten?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="life" /><category term="about neha" /><summary type="html">Navigate the Favorites</summary></entry></feed>
